<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discouery of the abhominable delusions of those, who call themselues the Family of loue Wherein their false Christ, and false profession is plainely laide open; and all their grosse cauils cleerely confuted.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118690</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853897</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853897</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19298</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00544)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19298)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 579:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discouery of the abhominable delusions of those, who call themselues the Family of loue Wherein their false Christ, and false profession is plainely laide open; and all their grosse cauils cleerely confuted.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 17-99, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed M.D. CXXII. [1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>The imprint date is made with turned C's.</note>
                  <note>Preface signed: Written by those Christians who are falsly called Anabaptists.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A discouery of the Family of loue.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]⁴ A-F G² .</note>
                  <note>Signature to preface crossed out in ink.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Familists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19298:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19298:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVERY OF THE ABHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Deluſions of thoſe, who call themſelues the <hi>Family of Loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN THEIR FALSE CHRIST, and falſe Profeſſion <hi>is plainely laide open,</hi> and all their groſſe <hi>Cauils cleerely</hi> confuted.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PRO. 28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They that forſake the Law praiſe the wicked: but they that keepe th Law, ſet themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REVEL. 2.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But this thou haſt, that thou hateſt the workes of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> which I alſo hate.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed. M.D.CXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19298:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19298:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>AMong the many Tares that the Enuious man hath ſowen in theſe laſt Dayes of the world; there are two principall ones, by which he ſo preuayleth (among them that acknowledge a Chriſt) that hee bringeth many millions of ſoules to eternall perdition; which wee earneſtly beſeech may be ſeriouſly conſidered. One is: a perſwaſion he worketh in many, that if they haue the knowledge of Chriſt in wordes, and doe make a profeſſion of him with their lips &amp; mouth. and ſo are accounted Chriſtians by name, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſome obſeruations, which haue a ſhew of his ſacred Commaundements, although in deede and Truth they bee the inuentions of Men; this they thinke &amp; are perſwaded is Chriſtianity effectuall, and will ſerue ſufficiently to bring them to heauen.</p>
            <p>A ſecond is: that when the Deuill ſeeth he cannot preuayle with diuers in this perſwation, but that they ſee Chriſtianity is another thing, then a bare profeſſion of Chriſt; then by little and little hee throweth them vpon theſe fearefull rockes of Familiſme; to beleeue and be perſwaded, that true Chriſtianity, and the worſhip of God, is onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the heart, &amp; not at all in any outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or Bodily performance whatſoeuer: and that the knowledge of a Chriſt, who by his bodily Death ſuffered for our ſinnes, is needleſſe; which being effectually wrought in their hearts, they growe preſently to a loathing of the true Chriſt.
<pb facs="tcp:19298:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and the bodily obſeruation of all Chriſts Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for the gathering of his Church: for his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery: for his Worſhip: and for his Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and all the appertainings thereof: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and contending againſt all, that in the feare of God, ſtand for the maintainance of them. And not ſo onely, but alſo defend with a high hand, that men may be ſaued, without knowledge or Faith in the Blood of the man Chriſt; and that Chriſtians ought to ſubiect their bodyes at the Magiſtrates commaund, in all outward reuerence, at any Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous abhomination, Mahometiſme, Papiſme, or whatſoeuer, keeping their hearts to God: all which commaunds of the Magiſtrates, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count but Idle vanities, as ſhall be ſhewed.</p>
            <p>And for the ſpreading of theſe, and many other moſt fearefull thinges; the Deuill hath raiſed vp <hi>H.N.</hi> the moſt skilfull workman of this Craft: and for his Succeſſors (though botchers in reſpect of their Maſter) <hi>M.P.</hi> who calleth himſelfe the mighty Prince of the <hi>Hebrewes;</hi> and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant; who writeth thus:<note place="margin">Seruant of M.P. a true Certif. cap. <hi>1.</hi> ſect. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>It is not the pride of our manly being, that wee meane to be equall in this or that, but onely we meane God to be the very fame in</hi> M. P. <hi>and the ſeruant of</hi> M.P. <hi>that he was in</hi> H.N. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe hauing written diuers Bookes, many of which wee haue read, by which they haue gotten many Diſciples, eſpecially ſuch, as hauing knowne much truth (which vſually is accompaned with the Croſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:19298:3"/>Chriſt) haue not onely forſaken that truth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were enlightened, but now doe moſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blaſpheme it; whoſe vniuſt accuſation of vs, and proude boaſts, occationeth the publiſhing of this little worke.</p>
            <p>And although theſe eſpecially be delt with, yet there are diuers others (who will not be called Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts) that are deeply tainted with diuers of theſe things; ſome, called the ſcattered flocke, who agree with the former, <hi>that they may remaine in</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon,<note place="margin">A litle booke to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> pa. <hi>113.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and there mourne &amp; tarry, &amp;c.</hi> And what account they make of the Lords Ordinances, may appeare by that they write of Baptiſme,<note place="margin">In T.L. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſ. pa. <hi>5.8</hi>
               </note> which they ſay, <hi>is teares: teares is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water in Baptiſme, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another ſort there are, who although they haue not the name of Familiſts, in that they diſlike ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their blaſphemies, yet are dangerouſly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with one of their maine grounds: They cry out againſt outward Church: Miniſtery: Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: and Church gouernment: and feeke and ſue to the Magiſtrate for reformation thereof; which when they cannot obtaine, they ſubmit, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly perſwade others to ſubmit to thoſe thinges, (which being againſt their Conſciences) they cry out of, onely to auoyde the croſſe of Chriſt; and they perſwade the people, that ſeeing they haue had comfort in that eſtate, although the thinges they practice be moſt vile, yet they may remaine in the practice thereof: and they being reproued for ſpeaking euill of that they practice, and ſubmit to,
<pb facs="tcp:19298:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>they haue Fig-leaues to couer this their naked hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; and when the examples of the Diſciples and Churches of Chriſt are brought to reproue their courſes; they anſwer: Theſe were inuiſible Churches; the Elect in the outward Church; and diuers ſuch fancies, whoſe courſes herein, are met withall in this writing following.</p>
            <p>The meane betwixt theſe we deſire to walke in, not approuing it ſufficient for iuſtification, to haue a Fleſhly knowledge of Chriſt onely; or to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to any outward obſeruation or bodily ſeruice where the ſoule or affection is wanting: For in all the Ordinances of Chriſts Goſpell, <hi>nothing auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth but a new creature:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.15. 2. Cor. 5.17 Ioh. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>and if any be in</hi> Chriſt <hi>he is a new creature: &amp; none can enter into the kingdome of heauen, except he be borne again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we doe abhorre any hypocriticall conceipts, which indeed are deceits, where the knowledge and Faith of Chriſt after the fleſh, and thoſe bodily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations that Ieſus Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth, is diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and made of none effect; yea where in ſtead thereof any manner of Idol-ſeruice is ſet vp and outwardly reuerenced. Chriſt telleth vs, <hi>It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth vs to fulfill all righteouſnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 3.</note> in bodily waſhing or <hi>Baptizing:</hi> and <hi>as often as wee eate that bread of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.26.</note> 
               <hi>and drinke that Cup, we ſhew forth the Lords death, till hee come.</hi> God hath made our Bodies, redeemed them, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.113.</note> and will glorifie them; ſo as we will glorifie him with both, in <hi>abhorring vaine inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:19298:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>and louing his Law.</hi> Chriſt hath coupled ſoule and body together, and let no man ſeperate them, in his ſeruice. If bodily obſeruations be aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned in the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements of the firſt table con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the worſhip of God,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.38.</note> 
               <hi>which is the great Commandement:</hi> and that we may with our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes performe any worſhip, why is not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the ſecond Table, our duty towards man abandoned in all bodily obſeruations? and that our bodyes may ſteale, Whore, Lye, Murther, and what not? which thing the oldeſt Father of this Family doth not ſticke at, as is ſhewed. Pag. <hi>54.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In dealing with this wofull people, let none take offence that wee ſpeake ſharply to them, but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cauſes thereof. They haue bene and are the greateſt enemies of righteouſnes that euer were, faining a God, and a Chriſt, according to their owne fleſhly hearts: and haue more peruerted the ſtraight way of the Lord, then euer did any; and therefore we hauing Chriſt and his Apoſtles for our example herein, wee truſt none will condemne vs, but thoſe that are touched: for if any be offended at this our Diſcouery, it is teſtimony ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient what they are; wee mention the names of none, leaſt they ſhould haue colour to ſay we perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them. The wicked and hypocriticall <hi>Scribes and Phariſes for whom was reſerued the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Hell.</hi> Elimas <hi>the Sorcerer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.33.</note> Iannes <hi>and</hi> Iambres, Hymeneus <hi>&amp;</hi> Philetus, and all the reſt, whoſe fearefull iudgements are written; are not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:19298:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>wicked in their blaſphemies as theſe are, as ſhall plainely appeare; and therefore let all pronounce againſt them the iudgements that are written, that others may heare and feare, and doe no more ſuch wickednes.</p>
            <p>It is meerly for want of loue of the Truth that men are giuen vp to ſuch fearefull deluſions; from which, that we may be deliuered, let vs follow the Truth, and that in loue; which truth is contained in the holy Scriptures, and not in the Dreames of <hi>H.N.</hi> or any other.<note place="margin">Heb. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>In theſe laſt dayes the Father hath ſpoken by his Son</hi> Ieſus Chriſt; <hi>who was faithfull as</hi> Moſes.<note place="margin">Heb. 3.2. Act. 3.22. Mat. 17.5. Act. 3.23. Gal. 1.8.</note> Moſes <hi>ſends vs to him. The Father ſends vs to him. And hee that will not heare this</hi> Prophet <hi>ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> And <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall he be, that teacheth otherwiſe</hi> then hee hath taught by himſelfe &amp; his Apoſtles. <hi>And his Name ſhall be taken out of the booke of Life, that taketh from it,<note place="margin">Reuel. 22.18.19.</note> and the plagues which are writen ſhalbe added to him, that addeth to the wordes of this Sonne of God.</hi> All which the Lords mouth hath ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Thus haue we taken this paines for the ſake of thoſe that are ignorant of theſe things; to the and that they ſeeing the Pit, may be warned, and ſaued from falling into it; which God for his Chriſts ſake, Grant to euery ſoule. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19298:5"/>
            <head>A DISCOVERIE OF THE FAMILY OF LOVE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE wiſedome of GOD, not only forewarneth (plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Scriptures) <hi>To take heed of falſe Prophets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7.15</note> 
               <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers, in that many are gone out into the world;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.1.</note> but alſo teacheth to make <hi>their madnes manifeſt to all men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.9.</note> that their deceits and craftineſſe whereby they lye in wait to deceiue being made known, all may be preſerued from their ſnare, and <hi>bee able to denounce againſt them the Iudgements which are written.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 149.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our Sauiour telleth vs; that after the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thoſe dreadfull dayes of the abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Deſolation, men ſhall ſay, <hi>Loe heere is Chriſt, loe there is Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>beleeue them not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 24.22. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>goe not thither neither follow them,</hi> And if any ſhall ſay: he is in a Deſert, or in a ſecret place, <hi>Goe not forth, beleeue it not,</hi> For <hi>as the Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning commeth out of the Eaſt, and is ſeene vnto the Weſt, ſo ſhall the comming of the Sonne of man bee,</hi> euen that bright Comming, ſpoken of 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. For the conſuming of that man of Sinne. Where plainely wee are taught, that the way of the Lord IESVS in the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is plaine
<pb facs="tcp:19298:6"/>and manifeſt,<note place="margin">Eſa. 42.16.</note> 
               <hi>For he will leade the Blinde by the way that they knew not, and will make darknes Light before them, and crooked thinges ſtraight,</hi> and <hi>the light of the Moone ſhall be as the light of the Sunne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 30.26.</note> 
               <hi>and the light of the Sunne ſhall be</hi> 7. <hi>fold, and as the light of</hi> 7. <hi>Dayes, in the day that the Lord will binde vp the breach of his people, and heale the ſtroake of their wound;</hi> and thither muſt men goe that will finde <hi>Chriſt</hi> indeed, For <hi>all his wayes are plaine to him that will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>and ſtraight to them that would finde knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14.6.</note> and his <hi>Wiſdome is eaſie to him that will vnderſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But where obſcurity and darkneſſe is, a <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a darke ſpeach that thou canſt not perceiue, and of a ſtammering tongue that thou canſt not vnderſtand, thither muſt wee not goe, nor ſuch muſt we not follow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 5.5. &amp;c</note> For <hi>the pathes of a ſtrange woman are moueable thou canſt not know them; keepe thy way farre from her, and come not neare the doore of her houſe, for her feete goe downe to Death, and her ſteps take holde on Hell, ſhee waigheth not the way of Life.</hi> This were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, if there were no more, to diſwade all that will not wilfully periſh, from harkening vnto, beleeuing, or following, thoſe moſt obſcure, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate, and tedious deceipts of that people (followers of that oldeſt Elder, or ancient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer <hi>Henry Nicholas</hi>) who tearme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues <hi>the family of Loue,</hi> whoſe execrable blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies
<pb facs="tcp:19298:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>are broached ſo obſcurely both by words and writings (as hath been alwayes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by thoſe that haue had to do with them) that the depth of Sathan in them, is of many not eaſily diſcerned.</p>
            <p>Moſt true it is, they haue much more poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned this Kingdome in former times then of late yeares, at which times diuers diſcoueries and confutations hath beene made; but ſeeing now they ſpring afreſh, and that they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the Faith of certain, neare &amp; deare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs; as alſo that they haue challenged ſome of vs (with great boaſts and brags) to combat with them; and haue in Writing vnder their hands teſtified, that we walke in ſo many euils (the particulars whereof are hereafter named and anſwered) that none fearing. God may haue any fellowſhip with vs. In conſideration of all which, and to teſtifie our vnfained dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of their profeſſion, as alſo to cleare our ſelues of their vniuſt accuſations; we truſt no indifferent perſon will judge of vs otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wel, for thus publickly dealing with them.</p>
            <p>Therfore in the feare of God; with reuerence of his Sacred myſteries: with vnfained humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of our vnworthines: with loue to Gods truth: and a harty deteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is euil, we will proceed only to deale in ſuch things as we haue by the now <hi>Family,</hi> or their fauorites beene prouoked vnto. And firſt of their <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19298:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> That they holde another <hi>Chriſt</hi> then the man <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> who gaue himſelfe a Ranſome for all men, not onely <hi>H. N.</hi> hath publiſhed, but alſo the preſent Family in <hi>England,</hi> doe with ſtifnes iuſtifie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H. N. and the Familyes</hi> Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>H.N.</hi> their oldeſt Elder (or rather their <hi>God,</hi> as ſhall plainly appeare) hath thus written.</p>
            <p>This ſame true light is the Annoynted with the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Euang. Reg. Cap. <hi>13.</hi> ſect. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> which annoynted in Hebrew is named <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and in Greeke <hi>Chriſtus,</hi> he was alſo in times paſt called of certain <hi>Rabbins</hi> among the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">H. N. Chriſt the perfection</note> the Lord his Saboth. And they ſay that the ſame Annoynted is the 7th day in the <hi>Paradice of God,</hi> wherein God reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from all his workes, and is the <hi>(Perfection)</hi> the which alſo is very true, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And in the ſame Chap. thus: <hi>Oh that they yet now awaked and tooke heede in the worde of the ſeruice of Loue vnto this Gracious time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The word of the ſeruice of Loue is the Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>and gaue eare vnto the ſame, that they might vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their ſafe making, and ſo then bee rightly and according to the truth brought into the true being,</hi> that is vnto <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe, (ſpeaking in praiſe of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Prieſts) thus: <hi>Therefore they were ioyned with others in the ſeruice of the Holyworde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euang Reg. Cap. <hi>3.</hi> ſect <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they let paſſe the child-hood or the youngnes of the holy vnderſtanding, and grew vp according
<pb facs="tcp:19298:7"/>to the requiring of the ſeruice of Loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the oldeſt Father is H. N's. Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>vnto the manly agedneſſe of Chriſt, that is vnto the true being of the oldeſt and holyeſt Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe thus: <hi>Hereunto ſerue the Pariſh Prieſts, as to ſuch procurators or helpers forward of the Communalties,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euang. Chap. <hi>14.</hi> ſect. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for to beare a good care o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, and to witnes and teach them dayly the holy vnderſtanding of Chriſt; the oldeſt Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo thus:<note place="margin">Firſt exhort. of H.N. cap. <hi>12.</hi> ſect. <hi>22.34.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If yee will not that the wrath of God come or fall vpon you, ſo deale faithfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and his holyneſſe, and walke with your Spirit in the louely and vertuous being, faſten your mindes thereto, and build your righteouſnes thereon, for that is an eternall faſt ſtanding foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, whereon all Gods Prophets and holy ones haue builded, and is, Chriſt himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that <hi>H.N's.</hi> Chriſt is plainly by his owne teſtimony; <hi>The perfection in the Louely being,</hi> whereunto his Elders doe attaine, and not the man <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Concerning whome he thus writeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh alas, how great Contention and vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſputations hath there beene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euan. cap. <hi>18</hi> ſect. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>concerning the Conception of</hi> Ieſus Chriſt <hi>in the wombe of</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>and touching his Birth!</hi> but if they all which contended hereabout had knowne the power of God, and that alſo the myſtery of the minde and workes of God, had beene giuen them to
<pb facs="tcp:19298:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnderſtand, ſo ſhould they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verily not haue contended thereabout. For his Succeſſor wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus: <hi>Where it is come to paſſe that all ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Spirit is gone cleane away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of M. P. called the laſt trumpt. <hi>ſect. 12. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>there the minde is become a poore widdow: and the ſame widdow bringeth forth a Mayden to light, which will conceiue the holy thing comming of the holy Ghoſt, for then the power of the higheſt ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadow the ſame Virgin, and ſhe ſhall thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue God with vs, euen the deliuerer from all thraldome and bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We might alledge much more of their intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and tedious ſtuffo, but it is weariſome.</p>
            <p>According to which damnable Doctrine, his now followers affirme: <hi>That men may bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the workes of the Law; without knowledge or Faith in the blood of the man Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> yea they holde it a meere fable, and ſpeake of it with great contempt, that we looke for juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with God in and through another; that we looke for juſtification without vs; that we ſpeake of imputatiue righteouſnes; that wee holde juſtification by beleeuing; for in truth they doe not hold that <hi>Chriſts</hi> Death &amp; blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed hath purchaſed any man; but that he was an example to vs and ſuch like; for they holde that thoſe Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. kept the Law, which (ſay they) <hi>was the Chriſt within them,</hi> and thoſe by this <hi>Chriſt,</hi> namely by keeping the Law were juſtified.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19298:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Which deteſtable blaſphemies of <hi>H.N.</hi> and his followers, (of making <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be a power and perfection in man, which is his juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) might rather be wondred at then confuted, were it not that the Deuill in his inſtruments transformeth himſelfe into an Angell of light, to deceiue the hearts of the ſimple, for whoſe cauſe we haue endeauored to ſay ſomething.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What Ieſus Chriſt is; for whome hee hath endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all his ſufferings; without Faith in whome, no ſoule can haue ſaluation.</head>
               <p>THat <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſignifieth a Sauiour,<note place="margin">Math. 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> annoynted; ſo that he is the annoynted Sauiour, to ſaue his people from their ſinnes, is ſufficiently knowne euery where in the Scripture.</p>
               <p>And although <hi>hee be God ouer all Bleſſed for euer,</hi> yet alſo is he true man, <hi>ordayned before the foundation of the world, promiſed to</hi> Adam <hi>when he had ſinned,</hi> and to <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Fathers.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Prophets</hi> alſo declare the certainty here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>A Virgin ſhall Conceiue and beare a Sonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 7.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhee ſhall call his name, God with vs. Vnto vs a Childe is borne, vnto vs a Sonne is giuen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 9.6.</note> 
                  <hi>hee ſhall call his name Wonderfull, Counſellor, the mighty God, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>a Woman ſhall compaſſe a man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 31.22.</note> And <hi>in the fulneſſe of time God ſent his Son made of a Woman, &amp;c.</hi> This Sonne of God thus
<pb facs="tcp:19298:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>made Fleſh, <hi>dwelt dmong vs,</hi> being ſent of the Father to declare and doe his will; in which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate <hi>(being like to vs in all thinges Sinne excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted)</hi> he ſuffered not onely the curſed Death of the Croſſe,<note place="margin">Reuel. 19.15.</note> but <hi>alſo trode the winepreſſe of the wrath of God,</hi> the agony of which was ſo great, that he not onely <hi>ſweat drops of Blood,</hi> but alſo cryed,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.46.</note> 
                  <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me:</hi> and <hi>if it be poſſible let this Cup paſſe from me.</hi> This being the true <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> that <hi>came by Water &amp; Blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.6.</note> witneſſed <hi>by the Spirit of truth;</hi> thus ordayned, promiſed, Propheſied of, and performed; And now if it bee proued, that what he did, hee did it in Obedience to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet for the benefit of others, &amp; that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledge of, and Faith in him no ſoule euer was or can be ſaued; we ſay if theſe thinges be plainely proued, that curſed fiction of the <hi>Chriſt</hi> of <hi>H. N.</hi> and his followers will appeare to be moſt abhominable.</p>
               <p>Therefore firſt will wee proue that <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſufferings were for others. That hee dyed for ſinne is manifeſt. That himſelfe had no ſinne, is as manifeſt; therefore of neceſſity he muſt dye for the ſinnes of others. That he dyed for ſinne is proued. <hi>Yet the Lord would breake him, and make him ſubject to infirmities, when hee ſhall make his ſoule an Offering for ſinne, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 53.10. Heb. 9.10 c. 1. Pet. 3.18.</note> All the ſinne Offerings were types of his ſufferings for <hi>Sinne,</hi> and he once ſuffered for ſinnes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19298:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> That hee had no ſinne himſelfe, is proued; <hi>Though he had done no wickednes neither was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deceit in his mouth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 53.9. 2. Cor. 5.21</note> 
                  <hi>For hee hath made him to be Sinne for vs, that knewe no ſinne, &amp;c. But was in all thinges tempted in like ſort,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>yet without Sinne;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.19. and 2.22.</note> He was <hi>that Lambe of God vndefiled and without ſpot. Hee did no ſinne, neither was guile found in his mouth, hee was that iuſt one,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>who appeared to take away our ſinnes, and in him is no ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he ſuffered for the ſinnes of others, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though what is ſaid be proofe ſufficient, yet if any thing might bee accounted plaine with theſe wofull men, manifold teſtimonies might be added;<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.5.6.</note> you ſee <hi>Chriſt appeared to take away our ſinnes; hee was wounded for our tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he was broken for our iniquities, the chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our peace was vpon him, and with his ſtripes are wee healed:</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>12</label> 
                  <hi>and the Lord laide vpon him the iniquity of vs all, hee powred out his ſoule vnto the Death: hee bare the ſinnes of many, and payed for the treſpaſſers: hee dyed for the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.6.8.9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>for Sinners: his Blood iuſtifies others: his Death reconciled vs when wee were his enemies: hee was giuen to Death for vs: for our Sinnes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.32. 2 Cor. 5.15 Gal. 3.13. &amp; 4.5. 1. Pet. 2.21.24.</note> 
                  <hi>hee dyed for all that were Dead: Chriſt redeemed vs from the Curſe of the Law, by his ſuffering, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the curſed Death of the Croſſe, that he might Redeeme them that were vnder the Law: who his owne ſelfe, bare our ſinnes in his Body on the
<pb facs="tcp:19298:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Tree,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18 &amp; 4.1. 1. Tim. 2.6. 1. Ioh. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. Chriſt the Iuſt ſuffered for the vniuſt: and he hath ſuffered for vs in the Fleſh: hee gaue himſelfe a Ranſome for all men: and hee is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation for the Sinnes of the whole world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, it is manifeſt that none can haue ſaluation, but by Faith in thoſe Sufferings of that man CHRIST IESVS.<note place="margin">Mar. 16.16</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and is Baptized ſhall be faued: as many as receiues him to them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>hee gaue power to bee the ſonnes of God, euen as many as beleeue in his Name:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>And whoſoeuer Beleeueth in him ſhall not periſh, but haue euerlaſting Life: hee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth not is Condemned already:</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>18</label> 
                  <hi>Be it knowne vnto you men and Brethren, that through this man is Preached vnto you forgiuenes of Sinnes; and from all thinges from the which yee could not be iuſtified by the Law of</hi> Moſes,<note place="margin">Act. 13.38.39.</note> 
                  <hi>by him euery one that Beleeueth is iuſtified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The righteouſnes of God is manifeſt vnto all and vpon all that Beleeue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.22.</note> And <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithfull he beleeued, and it was imputed vnto him for righteouſnes:<note place="margin">Rom. 4.24.</note> 
                  <hi>And to vs alſo ſhall it bee imputed for Iuſtice which beleeue: and the Iuſt ſhall liue by Faith:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.11.</note> 
                  <hi>And wee are the ſonnes of God by Faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>26</label> What ſhall we need to alledge more teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies? who will not wonder that any mortall man profeſſing the Scriptures ſhould dare to ſet his face againſt God in theſe his euident te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies; when God ſaith, <hi>The iuſt ſhall liue
<pb facs="tcp:19298:10"/>by Faith in his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> who dare ſay this is a fable, to ſeeke Iuſtice in another then in our ſelues? and that by the Law men may bee juſtified before God, as after it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare they doe.</p>
               <p>From all which teſtimonies we confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that neuer any Sinner was ſaued, but by Faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> either beleeuing him to come, by the Promiſe of God, to pay the ranſome for mans ſinne: Or that he is come to performe the ſame; For they that were ſaued before his Comming, did beleeue in him, according to the promiſe of the Father: but after he is come, all muſt beleeue (as himſelfe ſaith) <hi>That I am hee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 8, 24.</note> or elſe they ſhall dye in their ſinnes.</p>
               <p>All which is ſo euident that it may be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed at, that the Deuill ſhould ſo beſot men with blindnes; as that they ſhould contradict ſo euident a Truth; and the rather becauſe in wordes they acknowledge the Scriptures, and in their Writings plentifully quote them; but indeed it is certaine, it is but to blinde the eyes of the ſimple: For as the Maſter ſaith, <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is aſſuredly all falſe and lyes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">H.N. Dialog. cap. <hi>16.</hi> ſect <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſeducing and deceitfull, what the vngodded or vnilluminate men, out of the Imagination of their knowledge, and out of the learnednes of the Scriptures, bring forth; inſtitute, Preach, or teach. They Preach indeed the Letter, but not the worde of the liuing
<pb facs="tcp:19298:11"/>God. Let them eſteeme themſelues as holy as they will, they are all a falſe Chriſtianity, and a deuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Synagogue or Schoole.</hi> So ſay his Diſciples, <hi>That wee</hi> (out of the Family of Loue) <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not one word in all the vniuerſall Bible, and that wee are in the way of infernall darkneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that pretend what they will, they reiect all Scripture, further then may ſtand with <hi>H. N.</hi> and his fellow Elders in the Family of Loue. For thus further they write.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They ought to beware that, that they diſtruſt not the Eldeſt in the Family of Loue,<note place="margin">H. N. in <hi>1.</hi> exhor. cap. <hi>13</hi> Diuiſ. <hi>11.</hi> fol. <hi>31.</hi>
                     </note> nor ſuſpect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny manner of euill or vnwiſedome by him, nor yet in any wiſe perſwade themſelues that the Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, documents or Inſtructions, which are taught or ſet forth before them by the Father of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Loue, or oldeſt Elder, are too ſleight too childiſh, or too vnwiſe for them to follow after, or to obay, but with perfect hearts humbly and ſingly minded, as good willing Children, to receiue the ſame inſtructions proceeding out of the wiſedome and Councell of the Eldeſt, and to ſtand euen ſo ſubmitted till they come vnto the manly oldneſſe in the Loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, he ſaith: <hi>The Scripturely learned man hath no knowledge of Gods matters,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vnderſtand any tittle, much leſſe interpret or expound the ſame to others, it is giuen onely to the Family of Loue to vnderſtand the ſecrets thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, thus: <hi>My Children and you Family
<pb facs="tcp:19298:11"/>of Loue, giue eare to mee your Father, liue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my Doctrine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jn his <hi>1.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort. cap. <hi>11.</hi> ſect. <hi>1.2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that it may goe well with you, take heed to my Doctrine, and what I doe ſet forth and teach, that it may bee a Seale of life, and a witnes of truth in your hearts, for it is your Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And againe thus: <hi>Let your ſelues now in all your being, nature, minde, and diſpoſition,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Crying voyce cap. <hi>3.</hi> ſect. <hi>11</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>become renued through the loue in her ſeruice, and giue all your vnderſtanding captiue vnder the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Loue.</hi> And ſo teacheth his Children to ſay: <hi>O my Father in the Loue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Exhor. cap. <hi>13.</hi> ſect. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>I ſubmit my ſelfe and all my vnderſtanding vnder the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of thy Doctrine.</hi> Let all iudge if theſe wretches, aboliſh not the Scriptures, to ſet vp their owne deuilliſh inuentions, what ſhew of the Scriptures ſoeuer they make.</p>
               <p>But they obiect againſt this ſtrict Faith in this man <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his ſufferings. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 2.14.15. <hi>For when the Gentiles which haue not the Law, doe by Nature the thinges contained in the Law, hauing not the Law, are a Law vnto themſelues, which ſhew the effect of the Law written in their hearts, their Conſciences alſo bearing witnes, and their thoughts accuſing one another or excuſing.</hi> From hence they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidently affirme, that theſe Gentiles knewe not the man <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued on him, yet kept the Law, and thereby were iuſtified before God; and becauſe the Scriptures which they pretend to alledge to colour their deceits, doth ſo plentifully declare
<pb facs="tcp:19298:12"/>vnto vs a <hi>Chriſt,</hi> therefore they ſay: <hi>This is the Chriſt;</hi> for you muſt not imagine, that they ſay that any man can be ſaued without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yet they intend nothing leſſe in that ſaying, then that any are ſaued through the purchaſe of the Blood of that man <hi>Chriſt,</hi> apprehended by Faith, for that they count an idle Fiction, their euill Conſciences know we wrong them not herein; for we relate no more then what ſome of them haue vttered, in which we haue vſed much meanes to procure their reuocation of that their curſed conceit, that ſo we might not be conſtrained to publiſh it, but they waxe worſe and worſe euery day in their deluſions.</p>
               <p>Now to ſhew how they peruert this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to their deſtruction, let it be well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, what th'Apoſtle aymeth at in this place. <hi>Paul</hi> being the meſſenger of the ioyfull tidings of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1. cap.</note> in the former Chap. plainely conuinceth all the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to be vnder the wrath of God, &amp; that by not making right vſe of that knowledge which God afforded them, by the inuiſiblenes of his eternall power and Godhead, manifeſted and ſhewed vnto them by the wonderfull Creation of the world, which was ſufficient to make them without excuſe,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 19.</note> in that <hi>the Heauens declare the Glory of God, and the Firmament ſhew the workes of his hands, Day vnto day vtter the ſame, and Night vnto Night teach they knowledge, there is no
<pb facs="tcp:19298:12"/>ſpeach nor Language where their voyce is not heard:</hi> The <hi>Gentiles</hi> (we ſay) knowing God by theſe his wonders, <hi>yet glorified him not as God, neither were thankefull, but became vaine in their Imaginations, and their fooliſh heart was full of darknes; when they profeſſed themſelues to be wiſe, they became fooles, for they turned the Glory of the incorruptible God into ſeuerall Idols, wherefore God gaue them vp to their owne hearts luſts, &amp;c. they turning the truth of God vnto a lye, worſhipping and ſeruing the creature, aboue the Creator, and ſo not regarding to know God further by that meanes they had, God deliuered them vp to a reprobate mind, &amp;c.</hi> Th' Apoſtle ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing now conuinced the <hi>Gentiles</hi> prouing them to be vnder the wrath of God, he concludeth: <hi>O man whoſoeuer thou art thou art inexcuſable;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 2.1.</note> euen as well <hi>Gentiles</hi> as <hi>Iewes;</hi> and <hi>Iewes</hi> as <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which alſo in the 2. Chap. he goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to proue: For his feruent deſire of the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the <hi>Iewes</hi> maketh him to declare the eſtate of the <hi>Iewes</hi> to be as bad, or worſe then the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that they might ſee it, be humbled, and flye vnto <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> for although Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion in it time was profitable if they kept the Law, yet if they tranſgreſſed the Law, their Circumciſion was counted as no circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; <hi>And the vncircumciſion</hi> (ſaith th'Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>if they keepe the Law, ſhall, not their vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion bee counted for Circumciſion?</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>26</label> This
<pb facs="tcp:19298:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>was the glory of the Iew, that he was called a Iew, reſted in the Law, gloried in God, knew his will, &amp;c. This the Apoſtle ſeeketh to bring downe; by ſhewing them that; they that taught others, ſhould haue taught themſelues: ſaying, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>23</label> 
                  <hi>Thou that glorieſt in the Law, through breaking the Law diſhonoreſt thou God? For the name of God is blaſphemed among the Gentiles through you, as is written, &amp;c.</hi> Hauing now alſo conuinced the Iew, &amp; comparing the eſtate of the Iew and Gentile together, both which had the Law, th'one in the hart &amp; the Letter, th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the heart but not in the Letter, he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that the Gentiles did thoſe things by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which the Iewes did not obſerue by the Letter; whereby they were more excuſable then the Iew, being only a comparatiue ſpeach which is very vſuall<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 6.27. Ioh. 3.32. Luk. 14.26. 1. Ioh. 2.15.</note> in the Scriptures; not that either of them were iuſtified before God, for by nature or Fleſh, it is not poſſible to keep the Law; becauſe it is weake, &amp; by the works of the Law none can be iuſtified in his ſight.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle hauing thus done, demandeth this queſtion; <hi>What then? are wee Iewes more excellent?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>No in no wiſe, for wee haue already proued, that all, both Iewes and Gentiles are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſinne, as it is written; There is none righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous no not one,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>19</label> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. Now we knowe that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Law ſaith, it ſaith it to them that are vnder the Law, that euery mouth may be ſtopped
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19298:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>and all the world bee culpable before God;</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>20</label> 
                  <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the workes of the Law, no Fleſh ſhall be iuſtified in his fight; But now is the Iuſtice of God made manifeſt without the Law, hauing the witnes of the Law and of the Prophets, to wit,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>21</label> 
                  <hi>the Iuſtice of God; by the Faith of Ieſus Chriſt, vnto all and vpon all that beleeue: For there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>23</label> 
                  <hi>for all haue ſinned, and are depriued of the glory of God, and are iuſtified freely by his Grace through the Redemption that is in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>that he might bee a Iuſtifier of him that is of the Faith of</hi> Ieſus. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>26</label> Therfore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Wee conclude,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>28</label> 
                  <hi>that a man is iuſtified by Faith, without the workes of the Law; wee doe not make the Law of none effect through Faith,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>31</label> 
                  <hi>wee eſtabliſh the Law; For is the Law againſt the Promiſe of God? God forbid:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>For if there had beene a Law giuen which could haue giuen Life, righteouſnes had beene by the Law;</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>22</label> 
                  <hi>But the Scripture hath concluded all vnder ſinne, that the promiſe by the Faith of Ieſus Chriſt ſhould be giuen to them that Beleeue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.26. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>All are the ſonnes of God by Faith in Chriſt Ieſus; there is neither Iew nor Grecian, bond nor free, male nor female, but all are one in Chriſt Ieſus. Whoſoeuer is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Law, Chriſt ſhall profit them nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If men for want of loue of the Truth were not giuen vp by God to ſtrange deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Deuill, they would acknowledge their horrible error herein, giue glory to God,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19298:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſubmit to his truth, and confeſſe, that this in the Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. is Law, not Faith: Nature not Grace. They ſay, theſe were iuſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God by keeping the Law, but you ſee how plainely God contradicteth it, <hi>Gods Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is manifeſt without the Law;</hi> and <hi>the Law cannot giue Life.</hi> Theſe Spirits ſay, They did that by Nature which made them iuſt with God; when as God ſaith, <hi>Nature maketh vs the Children of wrath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3.</note> becauſe it cannot keepe the Law, and <hi>wee are ſaued by Grace through Faith,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> And <hi>wee are freely iuſtified by his Grace through Chriſts redemption.</hi> So that they doe as manifeſtly contradict God: take away Gods fauour, Chriſts iuſtice vnto vs through the Redemption of his precious blood, and fet vp mans merite for Iuſtice with God as euer the wicked <hi>Iewes</hi> did: but foraſmuch as they are ſo confident in it, let vs a little further proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute this thing.</p>
               <p>If euer any ſhould haue had iuſtice with God through workes, <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the righteous ſhould; but <hi>Abraham was not iuſtified by workes but by Beleeuing, that was counted to him for Iuſtice;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 4.2. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>now to him that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, the wages is not counted by fauour but by debt:</hi> So that if Iuſtification with God come by workes; wee are not beholding to God for it, he payeth vs nothing but our due; Oh feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full blaſphemy! But th'Apoſtle affirmeth, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19298:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>the promiſe made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> of being the Father of all the righteous, <hi>was not made to</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, <hi>or his ſeede through the Law, but through the righteouſnes of faith;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 14.16. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>For if they that be of the Law be heyres, Faith is made voyde, and the Promiſe is made of none effect: Therefore it it by Faith, that it might come by Grace, to them which are of the Faith of</hi> Abraham, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the ſame Apoſtle, who ſaith;<note place="margin">Gal. 2.15. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>we which are Iewes by Nature, and not ſinners of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, knowe that a man is not iuſtified by the workes of the Law, but by the Faith of Ieſus Chriſt, euen wee haue beleeued in Ieſus Chriſt, that wee might bee iuſtified by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, and not by the workes of the Law, for by the workes of the Law, no man ſhall be Iuſtified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore taking this deteſtable Doctrine as ſufficiently confuted, wee will conclude with the words of th'Apoſtle, <hi>We do not abrogate the Grace of God, for if Iuſtice bee by the Law, then</hi> Chriſt <hi>dyed for nothing,</hi> or without cauſe.<note place="margin">Gal. 2.21.</note> Oh that this Scripture might be conſidered! It is heere affirmed that if <hi>Chriſts</hi> Death make not men iuſt, but the Law, then Chriſt dyed for nothing, all other thinges purchaſed by <hi>Chriſts</hi> Death (if this be denyed) are counted nothing, and this is to abrogate the Grace of God.</p>
               <p>This their ſtumbling blocke from <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. being taken out of the way of all thoſe that will not wilfully periſh, the very foundation
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19298:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>their new <hi>Chriſt</hi> is plucked vp by the rootes: for there is not any Scriptures, that they haue hopes will make for them, although ſome haue alledged <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.9. <hi>This was the true the that lightneth euery man that commeth into the world;</hi> But we hauing anſwered, that this light is not any power in man, but that man <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.14. Ioh. 8.12. &amp; 9.5.</note> 
                  <hi>who was made Fleſh and dwelt amongst vs, &amp;c. who is the light of the world.</hi> This hath not been ſo much vrged: alſo ſometimes they alledge <hi>Cornelius,</hi> for proofe of iuſtification without Faith in the blood of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues faile of proofe, that he did not beleeue in the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> by looking for him for iuſtification; therefore they let it reſt concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this, and take it vp, vpon another occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which in due place we ſhall ſpeake of.</p>
               <p>Theſe weake and wreſted proofes, being the beſt that euer wee heard them alledge, for ſo great and weighty a matter; the taking away of the purchaſe by the blood of Chriſt, and therein mans euerlaſting comfort, they haue for the making of this more paſſable, and to haue the better acceptance (for indeed it is moſt odious to any Chriſtian heart) they haue (wee ſay) inuented this Poſition. That if men walke vprightly as farre as they ſee in morrall thinges, although they bee worſhippers of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, whether reall or mentall, through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and therein continue liuing and dying,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19298:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>they may be ſaued; which indeed is the ſame in effect with the former, as the wiſe may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne; For if men may be ſaued, that in words acknowledge, or not acknowledge the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> both being in workes aduerſaries to him, then what is the profit more vnto thoſe that beleeue in, and obey the Lord <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and thoſe that by word or workes deny him, If both may be ſaued?</p>
               <p>The wickednes of which, wee ſhall alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer plainely, through the Grace of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>No Idolater can bee ſaued, except they leaue their Idolatry by hearty repentance, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in, and obey Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>ALL fleſh deſires to finde an eaſie way to Heauen, and <hi>who would not dye the Death of the righteous?</hi> But whoſoeuer ſeekes Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by wayes of their own deuiſing, they ſhall not finde it. Indeed <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith; <hi>My yoake is eaſie, and my burthen light;</hi> but that is to thoſe <hi>who willingly deny themſelues, take vp his croſſe and follow him;</hi> otherwiſe, <hi>ſtraight is the Gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth to Life and few finde it, and many ſhall ſeeke to enter in and ſhall not be able. The gates of the heauenly Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> (the Goſpell, or new Teſtament, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24.26.) <hi>are open continually, they are not ſhut by Day nor by Night,</hi> Yea <hi>the Spirit, and the bride
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19298:16"/>ſaying come, and let whoſoeuer will take of the water of Life freely;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>And wiſedome cryeth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ſhee vttereth her voyce in the ſtreets, ſhee calleth in the ſtreet among the preaſe in the eate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the Gates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>and vttereth her wordes in the Citty,</hi> ſaying, <hi>O yee fooliſh, how long will yee loue fooliſhnes, &amp;c.</hi> So that there is mercy with God and plenteous redemption; but it is by the way, that God himſelfe, who is the giuer of it, will beſtow it; Is not he worthy to haue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of directing vs how to come to life, ſeeing hee himſelfe giueth life, and that freely of his fauour?</p>
               <p>The queſtion therefore now is, whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny can haue ſaluation, by their own wiſdome, walking in their owne wayes; or by the way, which the wiſedome of God hath directed.</p>
               <p>Wee haue already plentifully proued, if Scriptures may be proofe, That this is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of God (which whoſoeuer beleeueth not hath made God a lyer) and <hi>this is the Record that God hath giuen vnto vs eternall life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>and this life is in his Sonne. He that hath the Sonne hath life, and he that hath not that Sonne of God hath not life.</hi> So that if any will yet affirme that any can haue Eternall life, not confeſſing, nor beleeuing in the Sonne of God, they make God a lyer, whoſe record is otherwiſe: but this Record of God being beleeued, it doth declare all ſuch to be lyers, as affirme ſaluation
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19298:16"/>can be to any that Beleeue not in this Sonne of God. If God haue ſecrets which no man knoweth concerning this thing, we meddle not therewith; we know none he hath: but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that will of God which is reuealed in his ſacred Scriptures, we dare be bolde to ſay, no ſinner can be ſaued, but by Faith in this Son of God, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That no Idolater can be ſaued is thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. <hi>Confounded bee all they that ſerue gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Images, and that glory in Idols;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 97.7. 1. Sam. 12.21. Num. 25.2.9.</note> For <hi>they are not onely thinges of naught; and vanity;</hi> but <hi>they bring confuſion and curſe vnto all that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit vnto them.</hi> Yea the Lord ſaith, <hi>That Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters ſhall no more inherite the Kingdome of Heauen, then Adulterers, Fornicators, wantons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Buggerers, Theeues, couetous, Drunkards, ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, nor Extortioners: But Idolaters with the fearefull and vnbeleeuing, and abhominable, and Murtherers, and Whoremongers, and Sorcerers, and all lyars, ſhall haue their part in the Lake that burneth with Fire and Brimſtone,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 21.8</note> 
                  <hi>which is the ſecond Death.</hi> Therefore we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>to flye from Idolatry, and ſeperate our ſelues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and touch none vncleane thing, and then God will be our God and Father, and walke among vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.17 18.</note> 
                  <hi>and dwell there, and wee ſhall be his Sonnes and Daughters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hauing thus in generall proued that no Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later can be ſaued, that wee may come a little
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19298:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>nearer the thing, let vs obſerue how far Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try doth extend. It is ſufficiently knowne of many, that <hi>Idololatria,</hi> ſignifieth a ſeruice of any likenes, not onely of God, but alſo concerning the thinges of Gods worſhip, which is truely acknowledged by the annotation in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bible in Quarto, vpon 1. <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Babes keepe your ſelues from Idols.</hi> The wordes are: <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from euery forme and faſhion of thing, which is fet vp for any deuotion to worſhip God:</hi> And a great aduerſary of the Papiſts ſaith.<note place="margin">Dillingham againſt the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. pa. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>To ſerue God as we liſt, and not as he will, is Idolatry.</hi> So that any formes or faſhions of Deuotion in Gods worſhip, that is not Gods, or beſides Gods, are Idols; and Chriſts Babes muſt keepe themſelues from them, elſe they will bring them to deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as before is proued: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not onely they that worſhip ſtockes and ſtones as God, or as ſimilitudes of God, are I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, &amp; ſubiect to the Curſes pronounced; but alſo all ſuch, as in Deuotion to God ſet vp formes or faſhions to worſhip God by, that God hath not commanded; and this is plainly proued, by thoſe fearefull Iudgements pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt all ſuch as worſhip thoſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Idols, <hi>The Beaſt, or his Image, ſpoken of Reuel.</hi> 14.9. &amp;c. Which generally all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that theſe worſhippers doe in wordes worſhip the true God: For theſe Scriptures are applyed to thoſe people that in words doe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19298:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>acknowledge both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi> yet ſaith the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Theſe worſhippers, ſhall drinke of the wine of Gods wrath, and bee tormented in Fire and Brimſtone for euermore.</hi> Which eſtate of confuſion all muſt comeout of that will be ſaued; For <hi>as it is a habitation of Deuils,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 18.2</note> ſo the worſhippers therein, <hi>are worſhippers of Deuils,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 9.20</note> though it be in a great myſtery, and ſo percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of few.</p>
               <p>Next it remaineth to proue, that ſaluation is promiſed as to Faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as before is proued, vpon Repentance of Idolatry; as of all other ſinne, ſo alſo to obedience of Faith: not to obedience of the Law; but to obedience of the Goſpell, for that Faith that is not accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with Obedience,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> is not onely <hi>a dead Faith, but it is the Deuils Faith,</hi> &amp; that which ſhall neuer profit any man to Iuſtification. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Law had iuſtice in it felfe, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny could haue kept it: but obedience to the Goſpell hath iuſtice in Chriſt; to all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue &amp; obey him, who hath fulfilled the Law for them: and by the workes of the Goſpell wee are ſaued. <hi>For this is the worke of God</hi> (which ſhall inherite eternall life) <hi>that wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.29.</note> Which Faith is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with Obedience of * faith.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.5. &amp; 16.26.</note> It is written, <hi>Not euery one that ſaith vnto mee, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdome of Heauen but hee which doth my Fathers will which is in Heauen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 7.21.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:19298:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> And let it be well obſerued, that obedience to the Sonne, is not properly the obſeruing of thoſe morall precepts contained in the ſecond Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe,</hi> for that God hath from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning written not onely in the Tables of ſtone, but in the tables of mans heart; <hi>That as a man would another ſhould doe to him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 7.12</note> 
                  <hi>ſo he ſhould doe to him againe:</hi> and not that onely is written in euery mans heart, but euen this alſo, that man ſhould loue his Creator aboue all: but the manner of this loue conſiſting in obedience to his Commandements for his worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, that was directed in the Law by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Fathers, If the <hi>Gentiles</hi> would haue it, they muſt come vnto the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.2.</note> For <hi>to them were of credit committed the Oracles of God.</hi> But now in theſe laſt dayes God hath ſpoken (or declared what worſhip he will haue) <hi>by his Sonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>whome he hath made heyre of all thinges.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding all <hi>to heare him;</hi> who hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what manner of perſons, he accepteth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of: <hi>what his worſhip is: what Miniſtery he hath appointed: and what a Church Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hee hath conſtituted;</hi> and all other thinges for the well being of his Church; <hi>Which is his Body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.23</note> 
                  <hi>of which hee is the Sauiour, who ought to bee obedient to him in euery thing.</hi> And as the ſeruant <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Commandements gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by him, was worthy of Honor in that time,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19298:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>euery tranſgreſſion receiued a iuſt recompence of reward,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2.2.</note> of which we read of diuers dreadfull examples: <hi>Leuit.</hi> 10.1. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.19. 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.7.10. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.16. &amp;c. <hi>Num.</hi> 16. cap. 1. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 13.13. &amp;c. &amp; cap. 15. read <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.36.</p>
               <p>So is the Sonne worthy of more honour in his Commandements in theſe laſt dayes,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſoter puniſhment are they worthy of that doe tranſgreſſe them:</hi> This is the Kingdome,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> 
                  <hi>and power in Heauen and Earth that is giuen to this Sonne of God,</hi> to wit;<note place="margin">Mat. 28.18.</note> to rule ouer the bodyes and ſoules of men (whom he hath redeemed) by the ſcepter of his word. <hi>This is the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on his ſhoulder,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 9.6. Heb. 12.28. Act. 2.30. 1. Cor. 15.24. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Kingdome that can not bee ſhaken; On which hee ſits for euer to order it, euen till hee haue ſubdued all thinges; and deliuer it vp to his Father, and they that will not that he ſhall raigne ouer them,</hi> by his owne Lawes, <hi>ſhall be brought and ſlaine before him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 19.27.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now if ſuch be the eſtate of all thoſe that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not the Sonne in his Lawes, as if the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures be true it is: then what is the eſtate and condition of ſuch, as in ſtead of obedience to him, contemne his Commandements, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to mens inuentions for matter of worſhip to God? where now is place for that hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall pretence of walking vprightly as farre as they ſee? when indeed their walking is ſo farre from vprightnes, that when God <hi>calls and cryes vnto them, and ſtretches out his hand vnto
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19298:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>them all the day long;</hi> by that meaſure of means which he affoordeth them,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.21</note> they <hi>ſtill gaine-ſay him, and are rebellious againſt him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But their obiection is: That all they that are ignorant, and either by wordes, or workes deny <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and worſhip Idols, and ſee no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but thinke they doe well, they ſhall be excuſed: to which ignorant conceit wee muſt ſay ſomething.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ignorance ſhall not excuſe any that liue in Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and doe not obey the Sonne of God.</head>
               <p>THough it be ſufficient that the Lord hath pronounced theſe Iudgements againſt ſuch as beleeue not in, and obey not his Sonne, but are Idolaters, without exception of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or not ignorant; yet that the truth of the Lord may ſhine herein as the light at noone day, wee haue endeauored to take away this their obiection alſo, &amp; that in particular words.</p>
               <p>That ignorance is ſinne it appeareth by thoſe ceremoniall ſacrifices of attonement which were offered for it,<note place="margin">Leuit. 4.13 &amp;c. 22.27. &amp; 5.2.5.15.17. Heb. 9.7</note> and <hi>the wages of all ſinne is Death.</hi> Alſo the Lord ſaith: <hi>Harden not your hearts as in</hi> Meribah, <hi>and</hi> Maſſah, <hi>where your Fathers tempted me, &amp;c. though they had ſeene my worke, forty yeares haue I contended with this generation, and ſaid they are a people that erre in their heart, for they haue not (knowne) my wayes:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19298:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore I ſware in my wrath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 95.8. &amp;c. Hoſea. 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>ſurely they ſhall not enter into my reſt. And my people are deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for lacke of (knowledge.)</hi> And our Sauiour teacheth, <hi>That if the (ignorant) lead the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 15.14</note> 
                  <hi>both ſhall fall into the ditch. And hee that (knew) not his maſters will,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.48.</note> 
                  <hi>and yet did thinges worthy of ſtripes, hee ſhall be beaten.</hi> And <hi>they that kill Chriſts Diſciples,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.1.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall thinke they doe God ſeruice, becauſe they neither (knew) God nor Chriſt, which to know is Eternall life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> through his ignorance aduiſed Chriſt not to ſuffer, for which he had a moſt ſharp reproofe. <hi>Get thee behind me Sathan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 16.23.</note> 
                  <hi>thou (vnderſtandeſt) not the thinges of God.</hi> Againe, <hi>I know Brethren yee did it through (ignorance:) Repent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>that your ſinnes may bee put away. The Gentiles that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not to (know) God by his wonderfull workes, the Heauens and Earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>which preach and teach day and night to euery ſpeach and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and giueth euery reaſonable ſoule vnder Heauen a meaſure of knowledge, becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not to know God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.28.</note> 
                  <hi>God deliuered them vp to a reprobate mind.</hi> And the <hi>Iewes had the zeale of God, yet not according to knowledge, for they being ignorant of the righteouſnes of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10.2.</note> 
                  <hi>they found it not.</hi> And <hi>Chriſt Ieſus ſhall render venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in flaming fire vnto them that doe not know God, and obey not the Goſpell.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.8.9.</note> And thoſe that <hi>through the ſignes and lying wonders of the man of Sinne are deceiued,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.10. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſhall periſh and bee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19298:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>damned, becauſe they receiued not the loue of the Truth, but had pleaſure in vnrighteouſnes.</hi> What ſtore of teſtimonies are in this thing. If men doe euill though of ignorance, &amp; for the ſame ſhall not enter into Gods reſt: but be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: fall into the pit: be beaten: be deliuered vp to a reprobate minde: haue flaming Fire rendred vpon them: and be damned; all which the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken. If any notwithſtanding all this, will yet ſay Ignorance ſhall excuſe any;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.38.</note> wee will anſwer with th'A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>If any bee ignorant, let them be ignorant,</hi> and taſte the reward thereof.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of Ignorance is hardnes of hart, and vnbeliefe, and not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> want of means as is plaine. <hi>If our Goſpell be hid</hi> (that is, if any be ignorant of it) <hi>it is hid to them that periſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.3. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>in whome the God of this world hath blinded their mindes, that is, of the vnbeleeuers, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>they being ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the life of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.18.</note> 
                  <hi>through the Ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the hardnes of their hearts;</hi> So that vnbeliefe and hardnes of heart is the cauſe of Ignorance, and ignorance ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men ſtrangers from the life of God. <hi>Paul did it ignorantly through vnbeliefe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1 13</note> All haue, or might haue meanes enough, had they vſed that well which they had.</p>
               <p>And whereas they affirme it to be iniuſtice in God to condemne all the Nations of the earth, that haue beene or are ignorant of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Wee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19298:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>anſwer, though it be plaine that <hi>Chriſt is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by a meaſure of meanes to euery reaſonable Creature vnder Heauen:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1.6.23</note> For <hi>haue they not heard?</hi> Rom. 10.18. yet in this (th'Apoſtle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth) Gods iuſtice appeareth, that ſuch as had but <hi>the inuiſiblenes of God declared in the Creation of the Heauens and the Earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.19. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>which teach knowledge Day and Night, whoſe voyce is heard in euery Language vnder Heauen, &amp; they regarded not to know God by the ſame,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.1. &amp;c</note> 
                  <hi>God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vp to a reprobate minde.</hi> If any yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund why the <hi>Cannibals</hi> know no more; the Apoſtle anſweres, <hi>Becauſe they regarded not to know God by that they had.</hi> Hath not God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that <hi>if any ſeeke they ſhall finde?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 7.7.</note> What made the <hi>Wiſe men of the Eaſt, to finde the Babe Chriſt,</hi> but their diligent ſeeking?<note place="margin">Math. 2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Men finde not becauſe they ſeeke not;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 4.2.</note> wee need not goe amongſt the greateſt <hi>Pagans,</hi> we ſhall find too many, who know not God nor <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in our owne Nation; now the ſame cauſe they haue no knowledge, that is the cauſe why the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nibals</hi> haue no knowledge; namely, becauſe they ſeeke not. The <hi>Iewes</hi> had meanes enough, yet were they ignorant of the way of God, <hi>and God was found of thoſe that</hi> (in compariſon) <hi>ſought not after him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 10.20.</note> That none need be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, read theſe Scriptures. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6. &amp;c. 18.20. <hi>Math.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.2.3.</p>
               <p>Some alſo obiect: <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30. <hi>In the time
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19298:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>of that ignorance God regarded not, &amp;c.</hi> From hence they conceiue that God regarded not to puniſh Ignorance: but let the place be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and it doth effectually conuince that conceit. Th'Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to <hi>Athens,</hi> and beholding the blinde Deuotion of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,</hi> and reprouing them for the ſame, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth them of the true God, whome (ſaith he) you ignorantly worſhip, <hi>him ſhew I vnto you,</hi> and hauing ſhewed them what that God was, and what he was not: how he would be worſhipped, and how he would not: conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with theſe words, <hi>In the time of that Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance God regarded not, but now he admoniſheth all men euery where to repent, &amp;c.</hi> In the time of Ignorance God had no regard of your blinde Deuotion; but now in mercy, the knowledge of the Goſpell being reuealed to the world by his Son, hee admoniſheth all men euery where to repent, euen you <hi>Athenians</hi> of your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant worſhip, elſe as he had no regard in the time of your ignorance; you continuing the ſame, he will yet haue no regard of your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Deuotion: the like is ſaid of <hi>Caines</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>that God regarded it not.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.5.</note> God hath ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regard of Ignorance, that if his owne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements ſhould be performed without knowledge,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> it were ſinne; <hi>For without Faith, it is impoſſible to pleaſe God: and whatſoeuer is not of Faith is ſinne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14.23</note> &amp; the wages of ſinne is Death.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19298:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>This place therefore may be for confirmation of what is ſaid, to proue, that God hath no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of any ignorant worſhip whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>But their mayne obiection is from <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> in that he is called a <hi>Deuout man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 10. cap</note> 
                  <hi>and one that feared God, with all his Houſhold, which gaue much Almes to the people, and prayed God continually: a iuſt man, of good report, among all the Nation of the Iewes;</hi> The holy Ghoſt ſaith of this man: <hi>That his Prayers and his Almes were come vp in remembrance before God; Therefore</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>now ſend men to Iop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa, and call for</hi> Symon <hi>whoſe ſurname is</hi> Peter, <hi>hee ſhall ſpeake wordes vnto thee, whereby both thou and all thy Houſe ſhall be ſaued,</hi> This man (ſay they) was in the eſtate of ſaluation before euer <hi>Peters</hi> Doctrine came vnto him, which if it were ſo, it muſt bee by Faith in the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſeed <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and then will make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for them: where we can ſee a man or men, in whom wee can behold aſmuch good, as in <hi>Cornelius,</hi> wee will willingly ſay aſmuch of him as of <hi>Cornelius:</hi> But wil it therefore follow, that ſuch as liue in Idolatry, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully (though ignorantly) goe on in the ſame, that ſuch muſt be declared to bee in the eſtate of ſaluation? Seeing the Lord hath ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully declared the contrary: Can any ſuch thing be ſaid of <hi>Cornelius?</hi> wee neither reade that he was an Idolater, nor refuſed to receiue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19298:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt Ieſus when hee was offered.</p>
               <p>Thus much <hi>Cornelius</hi> eſtate proueth, That men that walke in no euill way, but on the contrary, haue many goodneſſes in them, God ſo remembreth and reſpecteth them, that hee will not leaue them, till he haue ſent <hi>Peters</hi> Doctrine vnto them, whereby they may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; yea God reſpecteth any good in any, as in <hi>Ahab:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 21.29. 1. King. 14.13. Ionah. 3.10 Rom. 1.12. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieroboams</hi> Sonne: <hi>Niniuie,</hi> yea in thoſe that haue no more but the workes of God to teach them, as euery reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vnder Heauen hath; that if they vſe that well; and glorifie God by that they haue, he will not leaue them till he haue brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Peters</hi> Doctrine, whereby they may be faued.</p>
               <p>Now that <hi>Cornelius,</hi> although a iuſt man, fearing God, and his prayers had in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance with God, was therefore in the eſtate of Saluation before <hi>Peters</hi> Doctrine came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, it may be queſtioned, if not abſolutely denyed, for theſe reaſons. 1. Becauſe, the Lord ſaith,<note place="margin">Act. 11.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter ſhall ſpeake wordes vnto thee, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by both thou and thy Houſe ſhall be ſaued.</hi> If they were in the eſtate of ſaluation before, to what end are theſe wordes ſpoken? 2. It is ſaid when Gods worke concerning <hi>Cornelius</hi> was declared vnto the Apoſtles, and the reſt of the Circumciſion, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>18</label> 
                  <hi>they glorified God ſaying, Then hath God alſo to the Gentiles graunted repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance vnto life.</hi> If they had life before, what
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19298:22"/>cauſe had they to glorifie God for granting it now by <hi>Peters</hi> Doctrine? 3. <hi>Peter</hi> relating that God <hi>choſe him that by his mouth the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> (<hi>Cornelius</hi> and the reſt) <hi>ſhould heare the word of the Goſpell and beleeue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 15.7.8.9.</note> 
                  <hi>For</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>God which knoweth the hearts bare them witneſſe, in giuing vnto them the Holy Ghoſt euen as vnto vs; And hee put no difference betweene vs and them, after that by Faith hee had purified their hearts.</hi> Now this being ſo, that by <hi>Peters</hi> Doctrine the ioyfull tidings was brought and they beleeued, by which Faith their hearts were purified, and then they were in the ſame eſtate with the faithfull; who dare be ſo bolde notwithſtanding all theſe manifeſt teſtimonies, as to ſay: <hi>Cornelius</hi> was in the eſtate of Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before any part of theſe came vnto him? Thoſe <hi>Iewes</hi> are ſaid <hi>to feare God,</hi> when as yet they had not repented of killing the Lord of Life; The humiliation of <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Neniuie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.5.</note> came vp in remembrance with God, as before is proued.<note place="margin">Act. 17.23. and 3.1.</note> The blinde <hi>Athenians</hi> are ſaid <hi>to bee Deuout,</hi> and the vnbeleeuing <hi>Iewes</hi> kept a conſtant courſe <hi>in Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe be the beſt proofes they haue, for a thing of ſo great conſequence, the iuſtifying of thoſe whom God condemneth: Saying, <hi>vnto the wicked thou art righteous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 13.22</note> 
                  <hi>thereby ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their handes that they cannot returne from their wicked way by promiſing them life.</hi> But
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19298:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>wee hope the Godly wiſe will reject the euill, and cleaue faſt vnto what God hath ſo plentifully and plainely taught, that Ignorance ſhall not excuſe any that continue in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; For if ignorance would excuſe men, how happy were the Ignorant? Or if one ignorant perſon, that iuſtifieth himſelfe in his wickedne? might be ſaued, why not two, and ſo twenty. and then where were the period to ſtay vs heere? Where were our rule, which Ignorant ſhould bee ſaued, and which not? Or how could it be auoyded, but all Ignorant perſons muſt be ſaued how wicked ſoeuer, if of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance? The reaſons for one (if there were any) would bee reaſons for all ignorant perſons whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>And for Concluſion of this thing, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: That generall repentance will ſerue from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12. <hi>Who can vnderſtand his faults? cleanſe mee from ſecret faults.</hi> To which wee anſwer, If there be any Repentance generall or particuler, we will not gaine-ſay it, for we acknowledge <hi>the righteous. doe offend oft</hi> in words and actions,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.22.</note> which they know to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, the particulers whereof are ſo many, that they are not able to vnderſtand them, and therefore ought they to pray, Cleanſe me from ſecret faults, that are hid from me, for want of remembrance, the particulers of which, if they were of could be related, they would particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19298:23"/>repent of them. But Idolaters that liue in Idolatry and take pleaſure therein, though of ignorance, cannot bee brought within this compaſſe. For let an Idolater who performeth any generall Repentance, let him be asked whether hee intend to include in his Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, his Idolatry which others know he liues in, his anſwer will be, no, in no wiſe. It is his Idoll which is his God, or God-ſeruice, which he accounteth one of the beſt actions that he doth; For example: Let one of the Family of Loue be asked (one that is not yet deified; for one that is deified cannot ſinne, and ſo needes no repentance) let a youngling in the Family be asked, whether in his generall Repentance, he doe include his bodily worſhipping, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtome of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or whereſoeuer he liueth, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate commaunding it, he will anſwer you no, he doth not repent of that, <hi>For hee ought to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect his Body at any worſhip which the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates commaunds, keeping his heart to God.</hi> For Gods worſhip is not at all outward, and therfore that his practiſe is good and approue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Doth he now repent of this in any gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality? which he accounteth one of his good actions? Repentance is an acknowledgement of ſinne, &amp;c. but an Idolater and Familiſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their action herein to be good, therefore cannot repent of them at that time.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19298:24"/>If <hi>any ſay they haue not ſinned,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. 2.35. 1. Ioh. 1.10.</note> 
                  <hi>God will enter into Iudgement with them, and their ſinne remaineth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh, but this is a dangerous cenſure (they obiect) not onely of thoſe that are liuing, but of many that are Dead. To which we anſwer, we cenſure none, onely relate Gods cenſure in his Word that cannot lye, <hi>Which word ſhall iudge all men at the laſt Day:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.48.</note> wee ſay of none, whether dead or yet liuing, that they are dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (except ſuch as ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, as many of the Familiſts haue) becauſe wee know not in what moment of time they may repent: But this we ſay; whoſoeuer they be that ſinne and neuer repent thereof, <hi>they ſhall periſh;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 13.3.</note> not we, but the Lord ſaith this. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo long as we know men line impenitently in Idolatry, through what deluſion ſoeuer, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to be reformed, and caſting Gods word behinde their backes, we can truely ſay they are in the eſtate of condemnation, and ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh if they repent not of that their Idolatry, and come into the <hi>Arke that ſaueth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.21.</note> which <hi>is the Baptiſme of Chriſt; the requeſt of a good Conſcience, by Chriſts reſurrection. For the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion that muſt be had and kept, is to draw neare to God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.22.23.</note> 
                  <hi>with a true heart in aſſurance of Faith, ſprinckled in our hearts from an euill Conſcience, and waſhed in our Bodyes with pure water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hauing thus diſcouered the falſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> of <hi>H.N.</hi> and his learners &amp; falſe way of Religion,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19298:24"/>of thoſe that are running faſt after him (though yet it may bee not of that louely Family) who affirme that by keeping the Law any may be ſaued, though they be neuer ſo great Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, (as Idolatry is taken of all but Familiſts) which wide &amp; brod way, of affirming that any may haue ſaluation, though they beleeue not in the man <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but be Idolaters, ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the vertue of <hi>Chriſts</hi> precious Death and bloodſhed; and all Religion and Godlineſſe. Wee ſay, hauing diſcouered the falſhood of theſe, wee now come to cleare our ſelues of their imputations, which followeth thus vnder their hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Twelue tranſgreſſions that yee (commonly called Anabaptiſts) doe commit euen with a high hand, and therefore yee for the very greateſt part are vn-Chriſtians.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, <hi>your greateſt Zeale is concerning Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and your leaſt is concerning Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes euerlaſting: and further yee contend againſt Godly ceremonies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this vniuſt accuſation are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained three thinges. 1. Wherein our greateſt zeale conſiſteth, namely in Cermonies. 2. Wherein it doth not conſiſt, in Godlines e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. 3. That we contend againſt Godly ceremonies. Firſt, what myſtery they may
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19298:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>conceiue in this word Ceremony (for they vſe it much) wee doe not well know, but if they had no other meaning, than as it is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> tranſlated, Religious Ordinances: or Diuine ſeruice, or worſhip: or Ceremonies: then we ſay, our zeale ought to be great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Ordinances of true Religion, or worſhip to God; for it is the firſt and great Commaundement.<note place="margin">Mat. 22.37</note> Religion or religious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, or worſhip towards God, conſiſteth in the vpright, hearty and vnfained ſubmitting vnto, with our Spirits, and performing with our Bodies ſuch Ordinances and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> the great Prophet hath commanded; <hi>For he that obeyeth not the Sonne ſhall not ſee Life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.36.</note> 
                  <hi>but the wrath of God abideth on him, and wee muſt obſerue all that hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, which if wee will not, wee ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed from among his people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 3.23.</note> 
                  <hi>for wee muſt ſtand faſt and keepe euery inſtruction which hee or his Apoſtles haue taught vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.2</note> 
                  <hi>for in theſe laſt dayes the Father hath ſpoken vnto vs by his Sonne, and if the word ſpoken by Angels was ſtedfaſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and euery tranſgreſſion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 2.2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and diſobedence, receiue a iuſt recompence of reward, how ſhall wee eſcape if we neglect ſo great a ſaluation?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>For the Sonne is worthy of more honour then the Seruant: wee are Chriſts friends if wee doe whatſoeuer he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth, but hee that ſaith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.14. 1. Ioh. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>hee knoweth God and keepeth not his Commandements, is a lyer.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:19298:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> So that if the Ordinances of Religion, or Diuine worſhip, be the Lords, if wee ſhould not be zealous therein, <hi>and earneſtly contend for the maintainance of that Faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iude. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>which was once giuen to the Saintes,</hi> we ſhould be iuſtly reproued of the Lord, as the Church of <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docea, and that iudgement pronounced,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 3.16</note> 
                  <hi>I will ſpewe thee out of my mouth.</hi> But they will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; the Scripture learned men haue no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, as in any other thing ſo in this; For the worſhip of God is altogether to be performed within, in the Spirit, and not in any outward Ceremony whatſoeuer. With this <hi>they flatter themſelues in their owne eyes, whileſt their iniquity is found worthy to bee hated, the wordes of their mouthes are iniquity and deceipt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 36.2. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>they haue left off to vnderſtand and to doe good; they imagine miſchiefe vpon their beds, and ſet themſelues vpon a way that is not good,</hi> as ſhall manifeſtly appeare, to all that haue eyes of any indifferency, when we ſhew what the worſhip of God is, as afterward we ſhall haue a good occaſion to ſpeake of; onely this may ſuffice to cleare vs from any vniuſt accuſation, if we be zealous for the Lords Ordinances concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his worſhip.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond part of the accuſation, that our leaſt zeale is for Godlines euerlaſting. What doe they meane by this Godlines euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting? whether that of their oldeſt Elder
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19298:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>H. N. the perfection of liuing in the holy vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and vpright righteouſnes in the louely being, which in theſe laſt dayes is reueyled by H. N. in the houſe of Loue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or doe they meane that to bee euerlaſting Godlines, which ſome of his young Diſciples affirme to be in thoſe <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Rom. 2. <hi>A iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in themſelues through keeping the Law, which they call the Chriſt;</hi> neither of theſe (we freely confeſſe) we ſeeke after; For the firſt we doe aſmuch deteſt as we doe the Deuill himſelfe, who is the Father of all lying allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and reuelations, that are not contained in the ſacred Scriptures: And for the ſecond we doe no leſſe abhorre to ſeeke Iuſtice in our ſelues by keeping the Law, for then <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed for nothing, and all that are bewitched with that curſed conceit, are aboliſhed from <hi>Chriſt</hi> are fallen from <hi>Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if they meant no more, but that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Godlines were <hi>to doe Iuſtice, loue, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and humble our ſelues to walke with God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Micah. 6.8. Mat. 22.37. &amp;c.</note> the ſomme of all which is, <hi>to loue God aboue all,</hi> by beleeuing to haue Iuſtice by the Death and bloodſhed of his Sonne, and obaying his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements for his worſhip; and louing <hi>our neighbour as our ſelues,</hi> wee vnfainedly deſire to ſtriue after theſe, and doe, according to our vttermoſt ability. And the Conſciences of diuers of theſe men, if they were not paſt fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19298:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>will not deny this, hauing formerly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the ſame by words and writings, not onely that our profeſſion leadeth to a holy life in our entrance, in our not admitting any but ſuch as manifeſt themſelues to vs to be new Creatures; but alſo in our progreſſe, wherein if any ſinne appeare in any, we haue power from the Lord Ieſus, and doe execute the ſame power, either <hi>to caſt the ſinne out of the party by Repentance, or to caſt the party out of our ſpirituall fellowſhip by Excommunication, as we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Math. 18.17. &amp;c. 1. Cor. 5.13.</note>. And for our dealings and carriages among men, we leaue that to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of them among whom we liue: wee had rather our actions ſhould ſpeake then our mouthes: Men full of weakneſſes we are, we freely confeſſe with vnfained humility, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſtriue towards perfection, wherein when we haue done what we can, wee ſeeke our perfection in and through the perfection of CHRIST, who is vnto vs all in all thinges, <hi>without whom wee can doe nothing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.5.</note> And this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting righteouſnes both towards God and man, <hi>the Ordinances of Gods worſhip</hi> leadeth vs vnto, though contemned of all Familiſts, in which the more zealous we are, the more doe we attaine to euerlaſting righteouſnes.</p>
               <p>To the laſt that we contend againſt Godly ceremonies. Their meaning is, (as afterwards they haue explained it) in that wee contend
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19298:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>againſt and ſubmit not with our bodies vnto ſuch obſeruations for ſuch Spirituall worſhip, as the Turke, the Pope, or any other Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or power, where we liue commaundeth. That we ſhould contend againſt all vaine inuentions (for Gods worſhip) and <hi>loue Gods Law.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.113.</note> The Holy Ghoſt teacheth vs: For if wee ſhould <hi>worſhip God by mens precepts, God would account vs hipocrites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 15.9.</note> 
                  <hi>and our worſhip vaine,</hi> but of this at large in his due place, in anſwer to their third taxation of vs, for not ſubmitting with our bodies to any outward ſeruice, keeping our hearts to God. This may ſuffice to cleare vs of the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Secondly, you are without the Charity deſcribed. <hi>1. Cor. 13.</hi> Chap.</head>
               <p>FOr anſwer to which, we ſay: The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Loue are many in that place, and therefore till we are accuſed particularly wee can giue no anſwer: We truſt if they come to particulers, we ſhould rather proue them to bee lyers and falſe accuſers, then that they ſhould proue ſuch things againſt vs; we know nothing herein by our ſelues, that men can iuſtly taxe vs, but we are not hereby iuſtified with God. But thus much we may truely ſay, that when our walking was no better then now it is; ſome of theſe younglings in, or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19298:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Family, haue ſolemnly proteſted, they neuer found the like loue as among vs, with any people that euer they knew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Thirdly, you ſubmit not to euery Ordinance of the Magiſtrate. <hi>1, Pet. 2.13.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO which we anſwer, they are falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers: wee giue vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> thinges which are <hi>Caeſars:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note> but <hi>Chriſt commaundeth vs alſo to giue vnto God thinges which are Gods.</hi> Now if we take away from <hi>Caeſar</hi> either by words or practice any thing that is his, we may iuſtly be accounted Rebels againſt <hi>Caeſar.</hi> And ſo all they that take away from the moſt high God, the thinges which are his, ſhall be accounted Rebels againſt the King of Kings, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee be patient and long ſuffering, and deferreth his wrath, <hi>yet if once it burne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh bleſſed are they that truſt in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The right knowledge of what is <hi>Caeſars,</hi> what is Gods, will be the beſt way of clearing our ſelues of this imputation, for concerning this, we not onely ſuffer the reproches of this wicked Family, and all their wel-willers; but alſo all our perſecutions are inflicted vpon vs for this cauſe. And without the diſtinct know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what is Gods: what is <hi>Caeſars:</hi> men ſhall greatly doe amiſſe. It is written here in <hi>Peter: Submit your ſelues to all Ordinances of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19298:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Man, for the Lord:</hi> So alſo in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. it is written: <hi>Yee are bought with a price, be not the ſeruants of men.</hi> In ſome thinges, we muſt ſubmit vnto them; and in other thinges wee muſt not ſubmit vnto them, for the Lord hath commaunded both; therefore it is meete we ſhould know the difference.</p>
               <p>If there were no more but theſe places of Scripture, they would ſufficiently decide the controuerſie. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, Submit your ſelues to all <hi>humane Ordinances,</hi> or to euery ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Man; a humane, or worldly Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance it muſt be, that wee muſt ſubmit vnto. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: yee are bought with a price, be not the ſeruants of men: Chriſt hath bought vs and therefore wee muſt be his ſeruants. This is confirmed in diuers Scriptures,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.4.</note> 
                  <hi>That we ſhould be vnto him that dyed for vs and roſe againe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.37.</note> 
                  <hi>For if we loue Father, mother, wife, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, or life, more then he, wee are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of him.</hi> And therefore did his ſeruants in the commaunds of God, when they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by the Magiſtrates ſay:<note place="margin">Dan. 3.16.18.</note> 
                  <hi>We are not carefull to anſwer thee O King in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Be it knowne vnto thee, we will not fall downe nor worſhip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 4.19.20.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. And we cannot but ſpeake the thinges we haue heard and ſeene. Whether is it better to obey God or men, iudge yee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In matters of God wee muſt ſubmit vnto Chriſt alone,<note place="margin">I am. 4.12.</note> hee is the <hi>one Law-giuer, able to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19298:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſaue and to deſtroy.</hi> The Father hath <hi>ſpoken by him in the laſt dayes, giuing him all power in Heauen and in Earth;</hi> Confirming it by voyce from Heauen, <hi>This is my beloued Sonne, heare him,</hi> and <hi>he that will not that he ſhall raigne ouer him, let him be brought and ſlaine before him.</hi> The truth of this moſt euident, not onely by the Scriptures but alſo acknowledged by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Superiours: the chiefeſt ouer vs on Earth acknowledgeth the ſame. The Kings moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Apol. for the Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance. pag.</note> 
                  <hi>I vtterly deny that there is any earthly Monarch ouer the Church whoſe word muſt be a Law, and who cannot erre by an infallibility of Spirit, becauſe earthly Kingdomes muſt haue earthly Monarchs, it doth not follow the Church muſt haue a viſible Monarch too: Chriſt is the Churches Monarch, and the Holy Ghoſt his Deputy: The Kinges of the Nations Raigne ouer them, but you ſhall not bee ſo, &amp;c.</hi> Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 22. <hi>Chriſt when he aſcended left not</hi> Peter <hi>with them to direct them into all Truth, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to ſend the Holy Ghoſt vnto them for that end.</hi> Theſe are his Highnes wordes.</p>
               <p>But the Familiſts anſwer vs; <hi>That Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> conſiſteth not at all in any outward obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: the which ſaying of theirs, if we ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, a great part of their tottering profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will fall, for they cannot deny, but we muſt worſhip the Lord our God, and him <hi>(onely)</hi> muſt wee ſerue.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:19298:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>adoro,</hi> is not onely taken for to Pray vnto, or to beſeech, but alſo to Honour, with bowing of the Body; and the Scripture expreſſeth the ſame. Firſt <hi>Math.</hi> 14.10. ſaith; <hi>If thou wilt fall downe and worſhip me. Luke</hi> ſaith of the ſame:<note place="margin">Luk. 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou wilt fall downe before me.</hi> Math. 8.2. <hi>And loe there came a Leper and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. Marke</hi> ſaith of the ſame:<note place="margin">Mark. 1.40.</note> 
                  <hi>And there came a Leper beſeeching him, and kneeling down vnto him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Luke</hi> of the ſame: <hi>And hee fell on his face and beſought. Math.</hi> 9.18. It is onely ſaid: <hi>There came a certaine Ruler and worſhipped him. Marke</hi> explaines it ſaying:<note place="margin">Mark. 5.22</note> 
                  <hi>Hee fell downe at his feete and beſought him inſtantly.</hi> The ſame ſaith <hi>Luke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 8.41.</note> not ſpeaking of any other worſhip. Againe it is ſaid, <hi>Math.</hi> 15.25. <hi>of the Cannanite, ſhee came and worſhipped him, ſaying Lord helpe me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 7.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Marke</hi> calles this worſhip, And <hi>ſhe fell at his feete.</hi> Further <hi>Marke</hi> ſaith, <hi>The man poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when he ſaw Ieſus ranne and worſhipped him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Luke</hi> calleth this worſhip onely this:<note place="margin">Luk. 8.28.</note> 
                  <hi>And hee cryed out and fell downe before him.</hi> Alſo thoſe wicked Soldiers are ſaid <hi>to worſhip our Sauiour, when bowing their knees before him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 15.19.</note> 
                  <hi>they mocked him.</hi> By all which and much more that might be alledged, it may moſt euidently appeare that the wiſedome of God that knoweth beſt how to ſpeake, and to teach vs, accounteth bowing of the Body, kneeling, or falling downe, to be worſhip.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19298:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> Further it is ſaid, <hi>And there were certaine Greekes that came to Ieruſalem to worſhip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.20.</note> 
                  <hi>at the Feaſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 8.27.</note> And the Euunuch is ſaid <hi>to come out of Ethiopia to worſhip.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſay, <hi>he came to Ieruſalem to worſhip.</hi> All which teacheth,<note place="margin">Act. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.11.</note> that the performance of thoſe ſerulces and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, that with their Bodies were to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, are counted Gods worſhip, and not only a Spirituall reuerence or adoration, which they might haue performed &amp; not haue come to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> This may ſuffice to proue, that any bodily reuerence in matters of God, and bodily ſeruices or Sacrifices are called Gods worſhip; and therefore vtterly forbidden in any Spirituall ſeruice, but onely in the true ſeruice of the true God. <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This therefore is to giue vnto God, thinges which are Gods, euen ſubjection with our ſoules and with our bodies, to thoſe parts of his Spirituall worſhip which he hath commanded in theſe laſt dayes by his Sonne,<note place="margin">Eſa. 2 8.</note> 
                  <hi>This is his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which he will not giue to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This the ſeruants of God knew ſo well, that they would not giue it to others, to the greateſt Potentates of the Earth, notwithſtanding all their commands and threats, And this through the power of God, wee will maintaine vnto the Death, and approue our ſelues to God and all good men, to bee neither Rebels to <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:19298:30"/>nor deſerue iuſt taxation but commendation herein of all, but hypocriticall and Atheiſticall Familiſts.</p>
               <p>And for what is <hi>Caeſars,</hi> wee vprightly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <hi>that all ciuill authority of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy is the bleſſed Ordinance of God, That all ciuill reuerence &amp; Honor ought to be giuen to it: That Tribute and all other duties are to be payed vnto it:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13. c.</note> 
                  <hi>That all ciuill commands of it, ought to be obeyed, And that of Conſcience to God, whoſe miniſters they are,</hi> euen from the King, to the moſt meaneſt Conſtable. And that they may ſo execute their iuſt offices, that they may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, walke with <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> be members of his Church; and be faued. That they <hi>haue a Sword giuen them of God to take vengeance on them that doe euill; and are ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God, for the wealth of all wel-doers.</hi> And this is all that can be <hi>Caeſars,</hi> or that wee dare giue vnto any mortall man whatſoeuer. So that hauing now ſhewed what is Gods; what is Caeſars, we confidently affirme, that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy may not be ſeuered from the foule or heart in our obedience to both, as theſe hypocrits the Familiſts doe ſuggeſt.</p>
               <p>In our obedience to man in all Ciuill things, that which we doe we muſt doe <hi>of Conſcience and not for wrath onely.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.5.</note> And <hi>Seruants</hi> (and ſo Subiects) <hi>be obedient to your Maſters according to the Fleſh; in all thinges, not with eye ſeruice
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19298:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>us men pleaſers, but in ſinglenes of heart, fearing God; and whatſoeuer yee doe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3.22.23. Ephe. 6.5.6</note> 
                  <hi>doe it heartily as to the Lord and not to men.</hi> Alſo <hi>with ſinglenes of your hearts as vnto Chriſt.</hi> All which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, That all our ſeruice to euery Superiour muſt be with the heart, and of Conſcience, and not with our Bodies onely: and for our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God with our Bodies, aſwell as our Spirits in all Spirituall or Diuine ſeruice, and that they may not be ſeuered therein, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: <hi>We are bought both ſoule and Body with a deare price,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.20</note> 
                  <hi>and therefore are commanded to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God with both. For our bodyes are the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Holy Ghoſt, and they are not our owne.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>19</label> 
                  <hi>And the bodyes of Chriſtians are the members of Chriſt,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>15</label> 
                  <hi>and theſe members of Chriſt (our bodies) muſt not be coupled to any Harlot.</hi> whether ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall or Spirituall; And <hi>wee are commaunded to giue vp our Bodyes a liuing ſacrifice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> 
                  <hi>wholy and acceptable, which is our reaſonable ſeruice of God.</hi> This is plaine to him that will vnderſtand. And the Familiſts teaching the contrary, it ſhall plainely appeare, they are not onely moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table hypocrites, but alſo Rebellious againſt the power of Magiſtracy.</p>
               <p>Magiſtrates that take vpon them to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund in matters of Gods worſhip, they doe not onely require bodily falling downe, but alſo Reuerence with the ſoule of heart.<note place="margin">Dan 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Did not <hi>Nabuchadnezzar require falling
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19298:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>downe and worſhipping?</hi> And doe not the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in Popery and elſewhere, where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint to worſhip is, doe they not require Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine adoration to their diuine Seruice as they call it? let all their Orders for their conſtrained and ſtinted ſeruice be looked into, and this cannot be denyed.</p>
               <p>And this being the Ordinance of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; if it be rebellion not to ſubmit with the body in ſuch diuine worſhip as they require, becauſe they commaund it, as the Familiſts affirme; then they are rebellious, becauſe they ſubmit not with their ſoules, ſeeing the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate requireth aſwell the one as the other. And hypocrites they are moſt notably; for they not onely practice this, but teach it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; they teach and practice, that in all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew and appearance, men ſhould doe that which in deed and in truth, they abhorre.</p>
               <p>And if this opinion be true; That we ought to be ſubiect in all matters of Religion with our Bodies, at the commaund of the higher powers, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. &amp;c. or any other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; then all perfecution for Religion is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, yea it is iuſt &amp; lawfull; For it is plaine, theſe higher powers are ordained of God to commaund that which the Saints are required to submit vnto; and whoſoeuer reſiſteth them there, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and ſhall receiue iudgement; for they are the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19298:31"/>of God therein, for the Saints wealth; and haue a Sword giuen them of God to take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of them that reſiſt them: therefore we muſt be ſubiect for Conſcience ſake; ſay wee, all theſe are inhumane Ordinances, as th' Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith in this place; ſay the Familiſts, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious ordinances outwardly &amp; bodily, which being ſo, then are they Gods Miniſters, The <hi>Turke,</hi> the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Magiſtrates, and all others, to command all outward ſeruice and worſhip, euen what they thinke good, and haue Gods Sword to take vengeance on all them that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them not: and it is for the Saints wealth, that they thus doe, and who reſiſteth them, ſhall receiue iudgement, and are not perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but iuſtly puniſhed. If this deteſtable dreame were true, then are condemned all the ſeruants of God in diuers Ages, that rather then they would either with body or ſoule ſubmit herein, at the Magiſtrates command, ſuffered many great afflictions.<note place="margin">1. King. 19.18.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſeauen Thouſand are condemned for not bowing the knee to</hi> Baal, <hi>and in not kiſſing him with their mouth. The three Children in not falling downe and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Image.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>The Martyrs of Ieſus that ſuffered beheading, becauſe they would not Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Beaſt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 20.4</note> And all that ſuffered thoſe cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell torments for not ſubmitting outwardly to that execrable Idol, the Sacrament of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> in times &amp; places of Popery. If they might
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19298:32"/>haue bowed, or otherwiſe outwardly with their bodies haue teſtified ſubjection, keeping their hearts to God, then did they all moſt wickedly and were the onely cauſes of their owne afflictions, which to thinke, much more to ſay were moſt accurſed.</p>
               <p>Againe, If it bee lawfull to bow downe <hi>(which is to worſhip as before is proued)</hi> with our bodies to an Idoll, who is a Spirituall har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, and yet that we may keepe our hearts to God, why is it not alſo lawfull to bow downe or couple our ſelues to a bodily harlot, and keepe our hearts to God, <hi>ſeeing Idolaters ſhall no more enter into the Kingdome of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>then A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers;</hi> And ſeeing the holy Ghoſt ſaith; <hi>He that coupleth himſelfe in his body with an harlot is one body with her,</hi> why is not hee that coupleth himſelfe in his body by bowing downe, or otherwiſe reuerencing an Idoll, one body with it? It cannot be denyed, but one is as lawfull as the other. And <hi>H. Ns.</hi> Doctrine will not contradict this, if it be conſidered. In his Booke called <hi>Documentall ſentences,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>13.</hi> ſect. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of temptations to ſinne, thus he writeth. <hi>If they take and lay holde on vs with force and violence, and that then although wee cry there commeth not any power or helpe vnto vs, for to withſtand them in their force and violence, and that they euen ſo rauiſh vs againſt our will, ſo are we guiltleſſe of the tranſgreſſing, for we cryed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19298:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be releaſed of the tyranny of the euill, and there is no helpe come vnto vs; of which guiltles tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing, the Law likewiſe witneſſeth,</hi> where it ſaith; <hi>A woman which is violently taken in the Field, whereas there is not any helpe, and ſo raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and although ſhee haue cryed aloude, yet got no helpe, ſhee ſhall be guil: leſſe of the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, &amp;c.</hi> So that the rule of theſe hypocriticall Libertines is come to a good paſſe with them, it is not ſinne to couple themſelues to Idols, which are Spirituall harlots, by performing all bodily ſeruice to them; alſo it is no ſinne to them to couple themſelues with a materiall harlot, if they finde no ſtrength (by praying) to withſtand the temptation; An acceptable Doctrine to all Libertines: who would not be of this Religion?</p>
               <p>But what truth was euer yet ſo apparant, but the enemy of all truth, the Deuill, would haue ſome objection againſt it? and therefore in this, his prompt Diſciples obiect; 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. From whence they collect this argument. <hi>If</hi> Paul <hi>became</hi> the <hi>all thinges, to</hi> the <hi>all men, that he might by all meanes ſaue ſome, to wit; in practicing with his body as the Iewes, or as them without the Law the Gentiles, in their Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall worſhip did, at that time worſhipping God in his Spirit: then ought we to ſubmit to all Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall worſhip whereſoeuer wee liue, in Turkie, Rome, &amp;c. a part of</hi> the <hi>all thinges;</hi> But the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19298:33"/>former is true; Therefore, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That this place they wickedly peruert, is moſt apparant, for there is no ſuch thing, as that the holy Apoſtle ſhould practice as the vnbeleeuing Gentiles did in their Sacrifices, or ſeruices, ſeeing himſelfe taught ſo earneſtly againſt it; <hi>Wherfore my dearely beloued flye from Idolatry.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>The thinges that the Gentiles ſacrifice they Offer to Deuils and not to God, and I would not haue you haue fellowſhip with the Deuils,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>yee cannot drinke the cup of the Lord and the cup of Deuils, yee cannot be partakers of the Lords ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and the table of Deuils,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 21.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Doe wee prouoke the Lord to anger, &amp;c.</hi> Who can deny this Cup, and this Table, and theſe thinges Sacrificed, to be bodily practices?</p>
               <p>But th' Apoſtle in this place, hauing proued his power fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> to preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, he ſhewes what a feruent deſire he had for the promotion thereof; for which labour he proueth by many reaſons he deſerued wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at the hands of the <hi>Corinths,</hi> and that hee had power to require the ſame, but he had not vſed it, but Preached the Goſpell of God free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therein making himſelfe a Seruant not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto them, but vnto all men, preaching the Goſpell vnto all men as they were able to beare it. To the <hi>Iewes</hi> who were vnder the Law, <hi>becomming a Iew</hi> by teaching them the Goſpell by the Law and Prophets which was
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19298:33"/>their owne Element, that hee might winne them. <hi>The Gentiles who had not the Law,</hi> Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2.14. <hi>As though he were without the Law,</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them God, and ſo the Goſpell not by the Law but by the Creation of the world, which they were acquainted with, as at <hi>Athens.</hi> Act. 17.22. &amp;c. <hi>That he might winne them that were without the Law. To the weake he became weake</hi> not giuing ſtrong meat to babes, teaching them as they were able to beare it, <hi>That hee might winne the weake.</hi> Thus as a skilfull workman, <hi>he became all things to all men, that by all meanes he might ſaue ſome,</hi> teaching all men the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> by thoſe means which themſelues acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he knew was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fitteſt way to conuince them &amp; conuert them. And not to make them beleeue that he worſhipped their dumb Idols, by performing all outward reuerence to them, as theſe Children of the Deuill, and enemies of all righteouſnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeeke to peruert the ſtraight wayes of the Lord, would perſwade; for that had beene to haue ſtrengthened them in their wicked Idolatry, that they could not haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from it.</p>
               <p>But firſt they bring for proofe of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> Paul <hi>Circumciſing of</hi> Timothy:<note place="margin">Act. 16.3. &amp; 21.26.</note> 
                  <hi>and purifying of himſelfe and others with him,</hi> to pleaſe the <hi>Iewes,</hi> Therefore (ſay they) may we doe ſo to all; to which we anſwer. God who had giuen to his owne people his own Ordinances, which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19298:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>were to bring them to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was come, &amp; many beleeued on him, yet were zealous of the Law, in that it was of Gods owne appointment, the Almighty Law-giuer in mercy reſpecting the weaknes of the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Iewes,</hi> directed his ſeruant the Apoſtle to obſerue ſome of thoſe Lawes, <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>purifying</hi> for the preſent, till they could be brought to ſee the end of them; yet taught the beleeuing Gentiles,<note place="margin">Act. 21.25.</note> 
                  <hi>that they ſhould obſerue no ſuch thing;</hi> For if they ſhould be Circumciſed, <hi>they were aboliſhed from Chriſt and fallen from Grace:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.3. &amp;c</note> and wiſhed that all thoſe deceiuers, that would perſwade the beleeuing Gentiles, to any ſuch courſe, ſhould be cut off, and beare their condemnation: yea when <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> by their example prouoked the Gentiles to doe like the Iewes,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.11. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul ſharpely reproued them to their face for their diſſimulation, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it was not the right way to the Goſpell.</hi> All which being confidered, what doth this make for the Familiſticall Gentiles, to performe all outward obſeruations in the worſhip of the <hi>Gentiles, Turkes, &amp;c.</hi> whoſe ſacrifice is the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Deuils? and is forbidden of God as before.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>They bring</hi> Naamans <hi>bowing in the houſe of</hi> Rimmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 5. <hi>And the Prophet bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him goe in peace, and therefore may they bow before any Idoll.</hi> Let the place be well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19298:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>It is a generall Maxime, That no expoſition of any one doubtfull Scripture, or collection from it, may be taken, which ouerthroweth many Commandements and examples that are out of doubt, which being granted of this hatefull Family, this their conceit will vaniſh. That this their collection is againſt expreſſe Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; examples, is proued: Firſt <hi>Exo.</hi> 20.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow downe, &amp;c. It was not lawfull to bow downe to</hi> Baall; and the Lord reſerued thoſe 7. thouſand to himſelfe becauſe they had not done it. The 3. Children would not bow downe, and were of God commended, &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the ſame; And in this of <hi>Naaman</hi> it could not be lawfull in him, in that hee asked mercy at Gods hands twice for it, which if it had beene good, he needed not haue done. So that it is moſt plaine, it was vnlawfull to bow downe, before the Idoll <hi>Rimmon,</hi> and therefore will not warrant theſe hypocrites in their cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; but it being ſhewed that this is not the meaning of the place, that the man of God pronounced Peace vnto him, in falling downe in the houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> for that they had beene both againſt command, example, &amp; <hi>Naamans</hi> repentance: we ſay it being proued, that this is not the meaning, let vs now find out what it is.</p>
               <p>Two thinges may be obſerued, that <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> required; one was: <hi>That</hi> 2. <hi>Mules loade of Iſraels earth might bee giuen him to Sacrifice
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19298:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>vpon to the God of Iſraell; The other that God would be mercifull to him in bowing downe, in the houſe of Rimmon, for his King to leane vpon and worſhip.</hi> The firſt of theſe was ignorant Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, for the Tabernacle or Temple, was the place of Sacrificing to the God of Iſraell, and not elſewhere<note n="*" place="margin">Leuit. 17. c. Deut. 12.5. &amp;c.</note>. The ſecond was no leſſe, if he meant to go on, in bowing in the houſe of <hi>Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and prayed God to be mercifull to him herein. And farre be it from the man of God to bleſſe him with ſalutation of Peace in either of theſe, which he knew to be expreſly againſt the Commandement of God; but goe in peace, trouble not thy ſelfe with theſe thinges, which will hinder thy peace, but being now cleanſed of thy leproſie, ſinne not againſt the Lord, which healeth thine infirmity, and his peace be with thee.</p>
               <p>Or it may be <hi>Naaman</hi> meant to teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Idoll when hee came vnto it, and prayed the Lord to be mercifull to him and ſtrengthen him in that point; for he profeſſeth, <hi>he will henceforth offer neither burnt offering, nor doe ſacrifice vnto any other God, but to the Lord,</hi> In which caſe, the Prophet might iuſtly bid, the peace of God be with him. Theſe are not contrary to the Scriptures but agreeable, and therefore may be accepted; But the other is moſt contrary, as before hath beene ſhewed, and therefore to be abhorred.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:19298:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> Thirdly, they ſay; <hi>To ſeperate from any that ſinne not againſt the Holy Ghoſt, is againſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> 1. Cor. 13. <hi>Loue ſuffereth long.</hi> In anſwer to which, the Lord ſaith; It is not loue;<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.17.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any ſinne to reſt vpon men,</hi> but expreſſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; and therefore Gods people are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>to rebuke men for their ſinne;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18.15. &amp;c.</note> &amp; if they will not repent, if they be of the Church, <hi>to auoyde them;</hi> if they be not of the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but vnbeleeuers,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.14 &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſeperate from them &amp; touch none of their vncleannes,</hi> as before is proued; and ſhal hereafter when this point is more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly handled. And this is loue, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſhamed, that they may come to repentance.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>They ſay Chriſt commands his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to heare the Scribes &amp; Phariſes,</hi> Math. 23. and performe ceremoniall worſhip with them, <hi>Goe ſhew thy ſelfe to the Prieſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What then? becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Leper to goe ſhew himſelfe to the Prieſt and offer the Offering appointed by <hi>Moſes</hi> for his cleanſing, which was Gods own appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; therfore hence doth it follow, that we may outwardly obſerue ſuch parts of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as the Gentiles who ſacrifice to Deuils appoint? <hi>Chriſt</hi> commandeth th' one; but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbiddeth th' other, as before hath been largely proued.</p>
               <p>As for hearing the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſes, &amp;c.</hi> All may ſee that theſe Familiſts rather then they
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19298:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>will want matter, they will ſay that which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth againſt themſelues. <hi>Chriſt</hi> teacheth that <hi>after their workes doe not;</hi> but theſe <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres,</hi> bring this Scripture to proue, that they may doe outwardly according to the wicked workes of the Gentiles, which is their offering to Deuils; Though our Sauiour heere expreſly bid his people, not doe according to the workes of the <hi>Iewes</hi> his owne people, if when he came they had not caſt him off. The moſt that this place proueth, is: that if Gods people teach truthes, but practice it not, the truth they teach muſt be followed, &amp; not their practices; but if they will not repent of their euill practices, they muſt be caſt out for being Gods people<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 18.15. &amp;c. 1. Cor. 5. c. 2. I heſ. 3.14.</note>, and ſerueth nothing to proue, that Gods people may practice according to the wicked workes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Idolaters, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; but of this expoſition more hereafter.</p>
               <p>But feeing this Scripture is alledged heere by the Familiſts, for proofe of that which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (that are not ſo farre gone as they) will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre; yet thus farre take it vp, as that they may heare Idolaters, in their Religious exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which is a dependancy of the former; we thinke it very neceſſary to ſpeake ſomething of that, foraſmuch as many haue beene ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne by that, vpon theſe rockes of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſme; for indeed in part it is the former. For it is this: a hearing of Idolaters to receiue ſome
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19298:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>Spirituall benefit by them, elſe why doe they heare, and yet in their hearts doe not joyne in any Spirituall fellowſhip with them, but iudge them to be Idolaters, &amp; their eſtate with God, to be moſt fearefull: In a meaſure it is hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie as the former, and vtterly vnlawfull by the Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That it is not lawfull to heare lying Idolatrous Prophets, except to reproue them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend againſt them, is thus proued.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe Lord expreſly forbiddeth it.<note place="margin">Deut. 13.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not hearken vnto the wordes of that Prophet, &amp;c. Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoaſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 23.16.</note> 
                  <hi>heare not the words of the Prophets that prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie vnto you and teach you vnity, they ſpeake the viſion of their owne heart, and not out of the mouth of the Lord.</hi> For if any goe to ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to aske for God,<note place="margin">Ezek. 14.10.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord will puniſh them with the Prophets puniſhment,</hi> Which is; <hi>to bee cut off from Gods people;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 13.9.</note> 
                  <hi>not to be written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the righteous; and not to enter into the Land of Iſraell for euer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſts ſheepe will flye from a ſtranger, for they know not his voyce;</hi> and they are often commaunded <hi>to beware of falſe Prophets which come in Sheepes cloathing;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 7.15. 1. Ioh. 4.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>the world heareth them, but they that are of God heareth vs,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>Lying Prophets are for the wicked;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Micah. 2.11</note> Gods people muſt not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceine
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19298:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>them if they come vnto them to teach them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Ioh. 20.11.</note> much leſſe may they goe ſeeke to be taught of them, <hi>Let them returne to thee, returne nel thou to them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 15.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. As Preaching or teaching the word of God, and hearing of the ſame among the Saints <hi>is a part of true worſhip,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.5. Math. 15.9.</note> ſo is preaching and hearing among the wicked <hi>a part of falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> and ſo their Communion. From which the Saintes are to ſeperate, <hi>and haue no fellowſhip with their vnfruitfull workes of darkenes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.11</note> 
                  <hi>but</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue them; And ſo the wicked themſelues account Preaching and hearing a part of their worſhip;<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.4. and 15.4. &amp; 26.4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>which the Saints may not offer,</hi> but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>contemne ſuch vile perſons and actions; and hate their aſſemblies, and not company with them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. As God commaunded that the Prophet <hi>that ſhould preſume to ſpeake a word in his name,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deu. 18.20.</note> 
                  <hi>that he commanded him not to ſpeake, was to dye;</hi> That is; the Iſraelites the people of God, were to ſlay his Body,<note place="margin">Deut. 13.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſo to take euill away forth of the midſt of them;</hi> So are Gods people now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, that euen among themſelues, they muſt <hi>marke diligentlys them that teach contrary Doctrine and auoyde them:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 16.17.</note> and <hi>from ſuch to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate themſelues;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.5.</note> yea <hi>if they were Angels from Heauen,</hi> teaching falſhood to <hi>let them be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.9. Gal. 5.10.</note> and <hi>beare their condemnation whoſoeuer they bee,</hi> which being practiſed towards falſe Prophets, within the Church, or without, the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19298:37"/>Saints are no more to heare them; but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their eſtate of Death; as vnder <hi>Moſes</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily; ſo vnder <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpiritually.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Saints are to declare vnto the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, That God ſaith, <hi>what haſt thou to doe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare mine Ordinances that thou ſhouldeſt take my Couenant in thy mouth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.16. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeeing thou hateſt to be reformed, and haſt caſt my wordes behind thee, and becauſe I held my tongue, therefore thou thoughteſt I was like thee, but I will reproue thee &amp;c.</hi> This <hi>is written for the Saints inſtruction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> that herein they may imitate <hi>their heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.48</note> For <hi>whoſoeuer heareth in Gods matters and is ſilent, he doth eſtabliſh that which is done,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 30.14.15.</note> 
                  <hi>And hee that wincketh at iniquity when he ſeeith it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 20.4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord will ſet his face againſt that man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Our Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.44.</note> would <hi>not ſuffer the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill (the Father of all lying Prophets) to confeſſe him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 1.25.</note> yea by his power he made the euill Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the man,<note place="margin">Act. 19.15.</note> 
                  <hi>reproue thoſe wicked men for med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the name of Ieſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.6.</note> And <hi>we muſt walke as hee hath walked;</hi> that when we heare the Deuill in the wicked falſe Prophets, meddle with the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or his holy word or Ordinances, we muſt ſharpely rebuke them, and aſmuch as in vs is, not ſuffer them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The end of the Saints hearing any falſe <hi>Prophet</hi> meddle with the word of God, muſt either be for edification or elſe to rebuke them as before, elſe what doe they there? If to rebuke
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19298:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>them, it is lawfull, as before is proued. If to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Spirituall food from them, they may not, for there is food ſufficient in Gods houſe, &amp; the Saints may not goe to <hi>Aegipt</hi> to ſeeke food of any <hi>Aegiptian.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 30.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Woe vnto the rebellious Children ſaith the Lord, that take counſell but not of mee, they walk forth to goe down into Aegipt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 31.1.</note> 
                  <hi>And woe vnto them that goe downe to Aegipt for helpe: For the Lord will ſay to his people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>how ſhall I ſpare thee for this, though I fed thee to the full, yet they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted Adultery, and aſſembled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in Harlots houſes:</hi> yea he doth further ſay, <hi>What haſt thou to doe in the way of Aegipt, to drinke the water of</hi> Nilus?<note place="margin">Iere 2.18.</note> 
                  <hi>or what makeſt thou in the way of</hi> Aſhur, <hi>to drinke the water of the Riuer?</hi> And therefore this Prophet of the Lord, when he had none to company with in Gods matters,<note place="margin">Iere. 15.17.</note> 
                  <hi>he would not ſit in the aſſembly of mockers, but ſate alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Chriſt</hi> hauing giuen ſufficient meanes in his Church, <hi>for the edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of euery member</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ephe. 4.16 Col. 2.9. 1. Cor. 1.7. &amp; 1. Cor. 3.21. 2. Chro. 11.15.</note> 
                  <hi>therin,</hi> it is high impiety for any of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaid members, to ſeek edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> in that it giueth that Honor and Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>. that belongeth to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Church, <hi>to the Deuill</hi>* by whoſe power that falſe <hi>Prophet</hi> teacheth; and the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his people of olde, that they being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from other people to be the Lords, <hi>ſhould beware leaſt they be taken in a ſnare after them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deu. 12.30.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. and leaſt thou aske after their Gods,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19298:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſaying, how did theſe nations ſerue their Gods &amp;c.</hi> So that Gods people may not go heare (which is to enquire) of any falſe <hi>Prophet,</hi> leaſt they be taken in a ſnare, by ſubmitting to that God, or that manner which that falſe <hi>Prophet</hi> teacheth.</p>
               <p n="8">8. As the word of God is holy, as other Ordinances among the Saints, for it ſanctifieth Church and all<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 17.17 Ephe. 5.26. 1. Tim. 4.5.</note>: ſo the word of God is more prophaned among, and by the wicked, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ordinances, becauſe they take it to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant their prophane practices; and if the Saints of God may not joyne with them in ſoule, or body, in any of their prophane courſes, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath bene proued; much leſſe in ſoules or bodies, may they joyne with them in vſing the word, which is moſt of all prophaned by them.<note place="margin">Luk. 10.16. Ioh. 13.20. Ioh. 8.44. Rom. 6.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. As they that <hi>heare Chriſts Prophets heare Chriſt, and they that diſpiſe them, diſpiſeth him;</hi> euen ſo they that heare falſe Prophets which are the <hi>Deuils,</hi> heare the <hi>Deuill,</hi> and they that diſpiſe them, diſpiſe the Deuill. Therefore let all that hate the Deuill, and would flye from him, ſo doe vnto his Miniſters.</p>
               <p n="10">10. It is the grieuous ſinne of any falſe <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> to meddle with the word of God, <hi>and his puniſhment is fearefull,</hi> &amp; it is no leſſe ſinne,<note place="margin">Ezek. 13.9. and 14.10.</note> and ſhall haue no leſſe puniſhment, in any that ſhal goe to aske or enquire of him for God;<note place="margin">Verſ. 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ſhall be both alike,</hi> For it is apparant, Gods people may not goe to aske or enquire
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19298:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>for God of any falſe <hi>Prophet,</hi> which they doe that goe to heare with ſilence, elſe (hypocrites that they are) what doe they there?</p>
               <p n="11">11. Falſe <hi>Prophets</hi> are ſtrangers from God, and we are commanded <hi>not to heare ſtrangers, but to flye from them:</hi> and it is the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Saints,<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>to examine falſe Apoſtles, and to finde them lyars,</hi> &amp; the Lords anger is againſt his people,<note place="margin">Ezek. 44.8.</note> when they <hi>ſuffer Strangers to take the charge of his Holy things,</hi> eſpecially of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Word, which halloweth all the reſt: and God demaundeth of his Sonnes,<note place="margin">Pro. 5.20.</note> 
                  <hi>why they ſhould embrace the boſome of a ſtranger?</hi> And <hi>what doeſt thou in the way of Aegipt? or what makeſt thou in the way of</hi> Aſhur? as before.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Gods people muſt not goe to the dead to enquire<note n="*" place="margin">Deu. 18.11. 1. Sam. 28.7. &amp;c. Eſa. 8.19.</note> which falſe <hi>Prophets</hi> are: <note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.2 Eſa. 29.9. &amp;c.</note> yea <hi>God hath couered them with the Spirit of ſlumber, they are blinde &amp; make ſuch blind as heare them, and their viſion is as the wordes of a Booke ſealed vp, &amp;c.</hi> And ſhall any ſeruant of God, goe to them to aske of God? ſeeing their eſtates is ſuch, and that ſuch thinges <hi>are an abhomination to the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deu. 18.12</note> 
                  <hi>which will cauſe him, to caſt vs out of his ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. A falſe <hi>Prophet medling with the Holy word of God poluteth it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hag. 2.13.14.</note> and <hi>the Lord will ſtretch out his hand to cut them off,</hi> euen <hi>all falſe Prieſts and Prophets that worſhip &amp; ſweare by the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zeph. 1.4.5</note> 
                  <hi>and that ſweare by</hi> Malcham; and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19298:39"/>his people <hi>to caſt away all pollutions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 30.22.</note> 
                  <hi>as a filthy cloath, and to ſay, get thee hence;</hi> which doing, this controuerſie will be ended.</p>
               <p n="14">14. It is as high iniquity, for a falſe <hi>Prophet</hi> to meddle with the holy things of God, which appertaineth not to him, but only to the Saints, as it was for <hi>Corah,</hi> and his wicked Company,<note place="margin">Num. 16. c.</note> to meddle with thoſe thinges of God which appertained not to them, but to <hi>Aron</hi> and his Sonnes; and the Lord will no leſſe puniſh falſe <hi>Prophets</hi> for their iniquity therein, then he did <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company: and as he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded all <hi>to depart from the Tents of thoſe wicked men, and to touch nothing of theirs, leaſt they periſh in all their ſinnes,</hi> euen ſo hath he commanded all to flye from Strangers, and falſe Prophets, and not to heare them, as at large before hath bene proued, leaſt <hi>partaking in their ſinnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 18.4.</note> 
                  <hi>they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in their plagues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas vſually hearing the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> is alledged for juſtifying of hearing falſe <hi>Prophets;</hi> which is formerly taken away, yet thus much we heere adde. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeat was the Chayre of Iudgement: <hi>Moſes</hi> was Iudge, not Prieſt; and the <hi>Phariſes</hi> were ſome of them of ſuch Tribes as might not be Prieſts, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome Scribes were Prieſts ſometimes. <hi>Nehemia,</hi> 8. And ſome Prieſts now are Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates) which ſhewes, that although Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates who of God haue the Chayre of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19298:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>be corrupt, and walke not as they teach, yet the people of God muſt hearken vnto the Law deliuered by them, and doe as they ſay, but not as they doe; and ſerueth nothing to proue the hearing of falſe <hi>Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For theſe <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſes</hi> are ſaid to teach truth, but not to doe accordingly, but falſe <hi>Prophets</hi> teach falſhood, &amp; therefore are called falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> plainely ſheweth, theſe were no falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> Math. 23. for falſe <hi>Prophets</hi> may not be heard as is before largely proued. And for <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Some preach Chriſt through enuy, ſuppoſing to adde affliction to</hi> Pauls <hi>bands,</hi> which was the Apoſtles ioy, that he was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy to ſuffer for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.41. not that he ioyed in the enuious preaching of <hi>Chriſt, that was miquity which hee ioyed not in.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.6</note>
               </p>
               <p>If any obiect that falſe <hi>Prophets</hi> preach ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent truthes, therefore may be heard, we anſwer. If they were Prophets of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> ſpeaking ſweet words in the name of the Lord, and teaching alſo in ſome thinges the viſion of their owne hearts, and not out of the Lords mouth, the Lord affirmeth, they bring no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to his people, and therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth them not to heare them. Nay they bring hurt, for they bring themſelues and all that aske of them for the Lord to confuſion, as before is proued.</p>
               <p>Further we ſay: and it is found moſt true,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19298:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>that the more truthes they bring, they deceiue the more, and inthrall their hearers vnder their bondage: For the leſſe truthes that falſe <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> haue, the leſſe they deceiue, as all may ſee, &amp; are moſt rejected of thoſe that haue any Religion, euen ſo ſhould the cunningeſt falſe <hi>Prophet</hi> be, if they ſhould teach falſhood only. Theſe <hi>are their ſtollen waters,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 9.17. &amp; 7.21. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>and hid bread that allureth the paſſers by, to runne after them:</hi> and herein is the myſterie ſo cloaked, that few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it. Why ſhould it be ſtrange to any God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.14.</note> that ſeeing the <hi>Deuill transformeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into an Angell of Light, and that ſo doe his miniſters, and perceiuing that by falſhood onely,</hi> he cannot continue his helliſh courſes of decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings; that he ſhould ſuffer many, or diuers truthes to paſſe, that vnder them, he might co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour all his falſhood? neuer falſe <hi>Prophet</hi> of whom we read of in the Scriptures, but they had ſome truths mixed with their falſhoods, to make them more paſſable; but let Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be wiſe, to try them that ſay, &amp; make ſuch great ſhew that they are <hi>Prophets,</hi> and are not, but doe lye, and let them declare vnto them, <hi>that their end ſhall be according to their worke.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And whoſoeuer will not receiue the loue of the truth, by thoſe meanes that God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, but will goe to enquire for God, and his Truth, at the mouth of falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome truth they teach; It is iuſt with
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19298:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Lord,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.51.12.</note> to giue ſuch vp to <hi>ſtrong deluſions, that they may beleeue their lyes and be damned.</hi> And again, none can heare or receiue any truth from them, but therein they heare, and receiue the Deuill, by whoſe power they teach, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is proued. Beſides they muſt alſo ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp all their falſhood and be ſilent, when they heare the Lord <hi>Ieſus</hi> in his holy Truthes blaſphemed.</p>
               <p>Thus it is apparant, neither hearing nor any other Spirituall action, may be performed with the Body, in which the heart and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is not preſent, contrary to this execrable and hypocriticall Doctrine of the Familiſts.</p>
               <p>Hauing now clearely refelled all the obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the hatefull courſes of theſe <hi>Baala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> and <hi>Nicholaitans,</hi> of proſtrating the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at any Worſhip, although it be the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, that ſacrifice to Deuils, &amp; not to God; or any other that although in words they profeſſe God, yet in workes they deny him. We may now proceed to other of their taxations of vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Fourthly, yee ſubmit not to Chriſts miniſtery, namely, thoſe which liue, and teach according to Gods word, and the Booke of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayer.</head>
               <p>IN anſwering of which: Firſt let it be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, who they account <hi>Chriſts</hi> Miniſters, concerning which; thus they ſpeake. <hi>To bee
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19298:41"/>called of God, is; to be raiſed vp to the worke of the Miniſtery; repleniſhed with guifts neceſſary thereunto; and to goe out vnder that outward forme, which God in that age wherein hee liueth, hath ordamed,</hi> viz. <hi>That outward forme which the Magiſtrate appointeth in Turkie, Rome, or elſewhere.</hi> So that with theſe <hi>Elimaſſes,</hi> they are called of God to the worke of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that haue ability to Preach, and goe out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the outward forme of <hi>Turkie, Rome,</hi> &amp;c. Which to ſubmit vnto, or haue fellowſhip with in any of their Spirituall ſeruices, ſo much as in hearing them, to receiue any Spirituall good from them; or any other lying <hi>Prophets,</hi> that runne, and God ſends them not; is vtterly forbidden, as plentifully hath beene proued.</p>
               <p>But the Miniſtery of <hi>Chriſt</hi> which is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his perfect Teſtament, to wit, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.1. 1. Tim. 3. <hi>c.</hi>
                  </note> we doe ſubmit vnto with all reuerence, in all things, according to the word of God.</p>
               <p>And for their mentioning the Booke of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer,</hi> this is but to colour their hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſre, that they might haue reſpect with authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for they might aſwell haue mentioned the Romiſh <hi>Maſſe</hi>-booke, or the Turkiſh <hi>Alcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi> as it; For they affirme that all Religions are lawfull, if Authority commaund them.<note place="margin">Seruant of M.P. in his natural wiſe man. <hi>2.</hi> Booke ſect. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> In theſe wordes; <hi>Euen ſo becauſe of Gods peace, yee ſhall ſubmit your ſelues vnto all manner of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19298:42"/>Religion, ſet vp by Lawes, wherein there is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Godlineſſe; for all ſortes of people cannot attaine vnto the true God ſeruice, at the firſt; Therefore yee ſhall not onely obey all Religions, not diſpiſing the Turkes, becauſe of their vnbeliefe; but alſo yee ſhall ſubmit your ſelues, vnto all Lawes and Authority of the Prince, from time to time, like obedient peaceable people. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring we are not appointed of God as Law-makers, and wee muſt be no Law-breakers, but Lawkee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; for if we breake the Law, and dye therefore, are we not guilty of our owne Blood? yes verily.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe thus; <hi>There are many vanityes vſed in the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſame in <hi>2.</hi> Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſect. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and it is both needfull and neceſſary, for vs ſometimes, to vſe our ſelues after their manner to liue in peace with them, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Fiftly, yee deny the Diſtinct degrees of Chriſts Miniſtery.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> YEe lyers are of your Father the Deuill: wee acknowledge the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct degrees of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Miniſtery, as before; but we deny the degrees of the Miniſtery of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and the Anti-chriſt <hi>Rome</hi>-and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that are not heard of in <hi>Chriſts</hi> Teſtament.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sixtly, ſome of you take in hand Miniſteriall workes, whereas not any one of you is called of God thereunto.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> VVHat it is to be called of God; with theſe Familiſts, we haue
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19298:42"/>formerly ſhewed, to wit; to be raiſed vp; to be guifted; and to haue that outward forme of calling which the Magiſtrates in <hi>Turkie,</hi> or elſe where ordaineth. Wee acknowledge that whoſoeuer doth take in hand, any Miniſteriall worke, and is not raiſed vp of God thereunto, and repleniſhed with neceſſary guiftes to the ſame, they doe moſt fearefully tranſgreſſe. Our Conſciences are cleare herein, that none can iuſtly taxe vs; but for going out vnder that outward forme the Familiſts ſpeake of, we doe deteſt it, as the Deuill, whoſe reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is vnto <hi>H. N.</hi> and his curſed followers. The true Miniſters of the Goſpell, are not <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of men, nor by men, but by Ieſus Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1.1.</note> neither by his immediate voyce from Heauen; or by that way which he hath ordained in his Teſtament<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 3. Tit. 1.</note>: and other outward formes for any Miniſter of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> know we none.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Seauenthly, ſome of you take in hand to Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, whereas yee are all without the teſtimony of Ieſus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> THat wee are all without the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>H.Ns.</hi> Ieſus or Sauiour, which is, the eſtate <hi>of perfection in the louely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or vpright righteouſnes</hi> as he calleth his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, vnto which onely his illuminate Elders doe attaine, which he calleth <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19298:43"/>before is proued, we freely acknowledge, and doe much loath and deteſt that deuilliſh ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but the teſtimony of the true <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> God ouer all, and true man, like vs in all thinges excepting ſinne, we bleſſe his Name, we haue, and purpoſe to holde faſt vnto the Death, of which, beſides what heere we haue ſaid; we are ready to render a reaſon, to any that ſhall require it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Eightly, yee are totally ignorant of the <hi>6.</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. <hi>Heb. 6.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> VVEE freely confeſſe if <hi>H. Ns.</hi> knowledge of the 6. Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. be true; we are totally ignorant of them. Therefore we will in ſhort ſet downe, from their owne mouthes and Pens what they vnderſtand of diuers of theſe Principles, and ſhew wherein we differ, and leaue them to the iudgement of the Godly wiſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, concerning repentance from dead workes, they teach: that none need repent of performing any bodily ſeruice to any Idoll, as before, but that they ought to continue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; making all the beholders conceiue, they doe as they, inwardly, and outwardly; when as they in their hearts, loath &amp; deteſt that ſeruice. And when they are come to the Family; they teach, <hi>they ſinne no more:</hi> For they write, <hi>That
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19298:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>in this Citty of Communalty, there is no more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spirit. land. Cap. <hi>33.</hi> ſect. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nor euill ſuſpition, nor yet ſight of euill in them; for within the ſame, one doth neither ſee, nor thinke any thing, but all good, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Concerning their beliefe of God, thus they write; <hi>See and marke yee beloued,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">H.Ns. mans falling away &amp;c. ſect. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning when God made all things well; then was the Lord one Lord of his Kingdome, and one God of his workes; there was alſo no more but one God, and one Man, and they were one, and had in all one order, being, and nature; For God was all that the Man was, and Man was all that God was.</hi> And elſewhere, thus he writeth;<note place="margin">H.Ns. Epiſt. to <hi>2.</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick.</hi> ſect. <hi>22</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>God had Created the Man, that he ſhould bee of one life, one being, one Spirit, and of one Nature with God, &amp;c.</hi> If this be the true Eternall, euerlaſting, vnchangeable, and incomprehenſible God, that had no other Order, being, and Nature, then Man, let all that know the true God iudge.</p>
               <p>And concerning their beliefe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we haue formerly related, that they hold not the Man <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that was conceiued &amp; borne of that Naturall woman the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> for that is a thing ought not to be ſtriuen about, but <hi>the Perfection of H. N. and his fellow Elders of that louely Family: or a Power in man, whereby they can keepe the Law, without Faith in the Blood of the man Chriſt.</hi> This is <hi>H. N.</hi> and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Concerning Baptiſine, This he writeth:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19298:44"/>
                  <hi>Let your ſelues in all your being, nature, minde, and diſpoſition,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Crying voyce Cap. vlt. ſect. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>become renewed through the loue in her Seruice, and giue all your vnderſtanding captiue vnder the obedience of the Loue; and humble your ſelues ſo vnder her ſeruice, to the end that yee all may become waſhed in the Loue, with the pure water of the Loue, for to become waſhed with her pure water, is the vpright waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the true Font of the Regeneration, or new hirth.</hi> So that to be captiuated in <hi>H. Ns.</hi> loue and her Seruice, is the vpright Baptiſme. And <hi>where that commeth not to paſſe vnto them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. to the <hi>2</hi> Daugh. ſect. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>there is not the Chriſtian ſeruice miniſtred, let them make themſelues ſo like faſhioned to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as they will.</hi> And for the Ordinance of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: he calleth that,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ſect. <hi>11.17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ceremoniall, Elementiſh, and mens owne Baptiſme.</hi> And <hi>M. P.</hi> that mighty Prince of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> as he calleth himſelfe, ſaith; <hi>Iohns Baptiſme is full of many great holy graue ſhewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M. P. bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light. Cap. <hi>13.</hi> ſect. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but in power weake as Water, he can eate no mans meat, drinke no Wine; ne ſtrong Drinke, therefore muſt his Head be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, for he ſhall not gouerne Diſciples ſtill; we were glad therefore to depart from him, for his going out, was the comming in of</hi> Ieſus.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Touching their opinion of laying on of handes we are ignorant.</p>
               <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">Euang. Reg. Cap. <hi>35.</hi> ſect. <hi>8.9.</hi>
                  </note> Of the Reſurrection of the Dead: Thus they write; <hi>Behold in this preſent Day is the Scripture fulfilled; and according to the teſtimony
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19298:44"/>of the Scripture, the raiſing vp, and the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Lords Dead, commeth alſo to paſſe preſently in this ſame day, through the appearing of the comming of Chriſt in his Maieſty; which reſurrection of the Dead, ſeeing that the ſame is come vnto vs from Gods Grace, wee doe likewiſe in this preſent day to an Euangelie, or ioyfull meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Kingdome of God and Chriſt, publiſh in all the world, vnder the Obedience of the loue; in which reſurrection of the Dead, God ſheweth vnto vs, that the time is now fulfilled, that his dead, or the Dead which are fallen aſleepe in the Lord, riſe vp in this day of his Iudgement, and appeare vnto vs in Godly glory, which ſhall alſo from henceforth liue in vs euerlaſtingly with Chriſt, and Raigne vpon the Earth:</hi> So that all may plainely ſee, the reſurrection from the Dead, is with theſe men, or rather Deuils, to get into <hi>H. Ns.</hi> Doctrine of the Loue. And becauſe theſe Godded men that are Godded with <hi>H.N.</hi> their God, doe dye aſwell as others, and being demaunded what becomes of their Bodies after their death? ſome of their young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings haue anſwered vs, they conceiue, their iudgement is, that the ſoule goes into God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſo beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth God; and their bodies lye and become as when they were not, which opinion may well ſtand with all their other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrations; For if the bodies riſe not againe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no queſtion they may aſwell worſhip an Idol,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19298:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>as the true God, and commit all their abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, for after this life, there is neither reward nor puniſhment for the bodies; Oh fearefull wickednes!</p>
               <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">Euang. Reg. Cap. <hi>3.</hi> ſect. <hi>2 3.4.</hi>
                  </note> concerning the Eternall Iudgement thus they ſay: <hi>When as now in this ſame day the wicked world becommeth Iudged with the Lords mighty hand, which wicked world is reſerued or kept in ſtore vntill this ſame day of the loue to the fire of Hell, for to be condemned in the ſelfe ſame day of the Loue, for euermore, to her eternall cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and iudgement of the fires cruell vehemency:</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>verily now in this ſame day when as now all vngodly and ſelfe-wiſe, with all vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant perſons, and falſe hearts of the Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, &amp;c. inherite with much ſmart and griefe in the vehement cruelty of the fire of Hell, the terrible condemnation, then ſhall the people of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spirit. land. Cap. <hi>27.</hi> ſect. <hi>11.12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>namely the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munialty of the loue, &amp;c. reioyce them in all loue, &amp;c.</hi> And further thus: <hi>After this time no time more; After the which there is no life more to be wayted for, for the ſame life continueth for euermore.</hi> This eſtate of <hi>H. Ns.</hi> loue and her Seruice, it is with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts the <hi>Chriſt;</hi> It is the Holy Ghoſt; the Baptiſme; the Reſurrection; the euerlaſting Life; the eternall Iudgement; and all in all: Of all which, wee are deſtitute, yet herein we haue knowledge, that they are abhominations fetcht out of the deepeſt pit of Hell, &amp; ſuch as
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19298:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>we are perſwaded, were heuer before vttered by the mouth of any mortall man.</p>
               <p>No maruaile now that <hi>H. Ns.</hi> Schollers ſay, we vnderſtand not one word in all the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Bible, and that we are totally ignorant of the principles of the Family, who to ſet a gloze vpon their wicked forgeries, abuſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. and other holy Scriptures, to their owne deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Hauing now diſcouered ſome of <hi>H. Ns.</hi> principles,<note place="margin">The ſumme of the true Faith.</note> wee will in ſhort ſet downe our Faith, concerning theſe 6. Principles, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Firſt of Repentance from dead workes, we doe beleeue, that <hi>euery tranſgreſſion of any Law of God is ſinne;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.4. Rom. 6.23.</note> and <hi>the wages of euery ſinne is Death;</hi> and ſo a dead worke: That no man <hi>by reaſon of weake Fleſh, can keepe the Law,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> and therefore by tranſgreſſion becommeth <hi>dead in Sinne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 2.1.3</note> 
                  <hi>and ſo by weake Nature the Childe of wrath: For the Law cauſeth wrath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>for where no Law is, there is no tranſgreſſion:</hi> but the power of Gods word, contained in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.34. Epheſ. 5.14</note> 
                  <hi>(and not the Reuelations or Dreames of H.N. nor any others) awaking man,</hi> and ſetting his ſinnes in order before him, and the fearefull terror of Gods wrath againſt him,<note place="margin">Act. 2.37. &amp; 16.30. Act. 2.38. &amp; 3.19.</note> cauſeth man to <hi>be pricked in his heart, and to cry out, what ſhall wee doe to be ſaued?</hi> To which God an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth; <hi>Repent of thy ſinnes; confeſſe them; ſorrow for them; and reforme them.</hi> But man
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19298:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeeing by the ſame holy Scripture, that this his repentance, or any other thing that he can doe, cannot appeaſe Gods wrath, nor ſatisfie his Iuſtice for his ſinne; he is inuited hereupon to flye vnto Gods <hi>Grace,</hi> by the Redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed through the blood of his Sonne, <hi>who is God ouer all, and tooke our Nature vpon him; and became Man:</hi> Dyed for vs: and <hi>is riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in his Body,</hi> aſcended into Heauen ſitting at the right hand of his Father, making inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for his ſeruants, euen for <hi>all that obey him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 5.9.</note> through <hi>whom alone wee haue Redemption euen the forgiuenes of our ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Thus by Faith in the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is this Sinner <hi>ſprinckled in his heart from an euill Conſcience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.22.</note> 
                  <hi>and muſt alſo be waſhed in his Body with pure water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. This <hi>is the Baptiſme that ſaueth, not onely the waſhing away the filth of the Fleſh, but in that a good Conſcience maketh requeſt vnto God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>by the Reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> Yet not onely the good Conſcience is Baptiſme, but alſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing with materiall water, into the Name of the Father, &amp;c. For <hi>to enter into the Kingdome of Heauen,</hi> which is the eſtate of <hi>Grace,</hi> or true Chriſtianity in this life, called the Kingdome of Heauen;<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.5. Epheſ. 4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee muſt haue Water and Spirit, Chriſt</hi> hath coupled them together, as <hi>his one Baptiſme,</hi> and let no man ſeperate them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By laying on of handes, wee conceiue is
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19298:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>meant the whole miniſtery of the Church, which conſiſteth of thoſe Offices mentioned in <hi>Chriſts</hi> Teſtament. All which, are to be entred into, by laying on of hands as theſe Scriptures teach<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 6.6. &amp; 13.3.</note>: For other laying on of hands, by which extraordinary guiftes were communicated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men; wee vnderſtand they were myracles giuen of God in the primitiue Church, for the confirmation of the Apoſtles authority, who taught thinges that neuer before were taught,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.5.</note> which that they might be credited, they did ſuch thinges as neuer men did; And if any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſt can doe Myracles as did th Apoſtles, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might they haue had ſome colour to write, and bring into the world new Goſpels, as they are not aſhamed to doe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Concerning the Reſurrection from the Dead; We beleeue that our ſoules ſhall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from our bodies by naturall Death; <hi>That the Body returnes to earth whence it came, and the Spirit to God that gaue it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.7 1. Cor. 15.</note> vntill the day that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſhall come againe to Iudge quicke and dead; Then ſhall our Bodies riſe againe, <hi>euen theſe bodies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 19.25. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>and with theſe eyes ſhall wee ſee our Redeemer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, we doe beleeue, and looke for to our great reioycing, the bleſſed appearing of our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> to that Eternall iudgement, <hi>wherein hee ſhall Iudge both quicke and dead ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their works done in this Fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10</note> 
                  <hi>whether
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19298:47"/>they be good or euill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 20.12.</note> to an Eternall being, to wit; <hi>Them that by continuance in wel-doing ſeeke glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Immortality,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2.7. &amp;c. 1. Theſ. 4.17. Rom. 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſhall come to Eternall Life;</hi> where <hi>they ſhall bee euer with the Lord.</hi> But thoſe that <hi>are contentious and diſobey the Truth, and obeyes vnrighteouſnes,</hi> &amp; haue done euill, and haue not repented thereof, <hi>They ſhall come forth to the reſurrection of condemnation;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.29.</note> 
                  <hi>indignation and wrath ſhall bee vpon them, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Lake for euermore with the Deuill and his Angels.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25.41.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now let all Iudge whether wee be totally ignorant of the 6. Principles, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. as theſe accuſers doe ſuggeſt; or rather that themſelues are not only ignorant of them; for if they were, their ſinne were the leſſe, but they deny them, and that after their enlightning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The 9. tranſgreſſion they accuſe vs of, is;</hi> Ninthly, you will not bee reformed by the Light which God hath manifeſted in theſe latter times, and whereof much is in the Booke of Common Prayer, and in the Homilies, and in the Booke of Ordering of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> VVEE hauing asked ſome of them, what Light this is, that in theſe latter times God hath manifeſted, for we conceiue God neuer ſpake, nor euer will, after his ſpeaking by his Sonne, in theſe laſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19298:47"/>dayes; who by himſelfe and his Apoſtles, hath deliuered all the Counſell of God, ſealing it vp with theſe ſentences. <hi>If wee or an Angell from Heauen teach any otherwiſe, then we haue Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1.8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>let him bee accurſed. And if any adde to what they haue done,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 22.18.19.</note> 
                  <hi>God will adde the plagues written by them; or if any take away any of thoſe their wordes, God will take away their names out of the Booke of Life,</hi> (we ſay) we hauing asked them, concerning theſe thinges, they haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered vs; God hath ſpoken to the world at three ſeuerall times; Firſt by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Fathers. 2. By <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the Apoſtles. And thirdly, by an euerlaſting Goſpell in theſe laſt dayes, alledging <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>Which what Goſpell ſhould it bee but the Goſpell of the Kingdome which <hi>H. N.</hi> hath publiſhed to the world; in which many of his poyſoned Doctrines is broached, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which hee hath giuen himſelfe a ſtately ſtile, farre exceeding the Apoſtles in all their writings, full of blaſphemies, which is this: <hi>H. N. through the Grace and mercy of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euang. Peg. Cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and through the holy Spirit of the loue of Ieſu Chriſt, raiſed vp by the higheſt God from the Death, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the prouidence of God and his Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: annoynted with the Holy Ghoſt, in the olde age of the holy vnderſtanding of Ieſu Chriſt: Godded with God in the Spirit of his loue: made heyre with Chriſt in the heauenly goods of the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19298:48"/>riches of God: Illuminated in the Spirit with the heauenly truth, the true light of the perfect being: elected to a Miniſter of the gracious word (which is now in the laſt time raiſed vp by God, according to his promiſes) in the moſt holy Seruice of God; vnder the Obedience of his Loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The blaſphemies of whoſe writings are ſo groſſe, as theſe wretches are very ſtrait to whom they affirme that this euerlaſting Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is <hi>H. Ns.</hi> the Light which God hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in theſe laſt dayes; yet apparantly it is it, and no other; For they ſpeake plainely to whom they dare truſt, as they know, wee well know; and diſperſe his Bookes to thoſe in whom they haue ſome hopes, requiring moſt ſolemne proteſtations that they ſhall not let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſee them, who they know to be aduerſe<note n="*" place="margin">For often they write, keepe ſecrets from vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers.</note>: So that it is plaine, this light which they much boaſt of, and haue tolde many of vs of, is this Goſpell of <hi>H. N.</hi> which is ſo farre from light, being compared with the holy Scriptures, that it is damnable darknes; from which, we truſt our God will alwayes keepe vs.</p>
               <p>But they tell vs, much of it is in the Booke of Common prayer, in the Booke of Homilies; and in the booke of ordering of <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> wherein all may ſee theſe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, ſtill would ſhelter themſelues vnder Authority, though it be a manifeſtation to all, of their owne hypocriſie; and of the horrible
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19298:48"/>defamation of the Common prayer Booke: for as wee ſaid before, they reſpect the Common prayer booke and the reſt, no more then they reſpect the Popiſh <hi>Maſſe</hi>-booke, nor the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh <hi>Alchoran,</hi> to wit, in reſpect of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates commaund; being farre from thinking in their hearts, that any of them containeth the worſhip of God, which they affirme to be one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inward, and not in any outward obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whatſoeuer: wherein they are moſt notable diſſemblers, in making men beleeue, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that which they doe not.</p>
               <p>And what a defamation is it vnto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer Booke, and the reſt, that they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme much of this new Light to be contained therein. Is any ſuch thing contained in any of theſe Bookes, as that <hi>men euer had, or can haue One Nature, Being, Life, order, and Spirit with God? That God is all that Man is, and that man is all that God is: That Chriſt is the Perfection in the louely being, whereunto H. N. and his fellow Elders doe attaine: That Regeneration or the true Baptiſme, is the captiuating of men into H.Ns. loue and her ſeruice: That the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the dead is the riſing to H.Ns. Doctrine: That the Eternall iudgement is in this Day of the Loue of H. N: and the life euerlaſting the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in the Doctrine of H. N. after which there is no life more to bee waited for: That any Idoll may haue all reuerence performed to it with the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19298:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>body: that a man being tempted to any ſinne, if vpon crying helpe come not, hee is free from the tranſgreſſing, though he commit the fact: That in this Citty or Communialty, there is no more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill nor euill ſuſpition, nor yet ſight of euill in them. For within the ſame one doth neither ſee, nor thinke any thing but all good, &amp;c. That this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily ſhould make manifeſt their whole heart with all their counſels, mindes, willes, and thoughts, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all their doings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Exhor. cap. <hi>13.</hi> ſect. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>dealings and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, naked and bare before the Eldeſt in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Loue, and not couer nor hide any thing (be it what it is) before him, alſo all whereunto their inclination, kinde, and nature draweth them vnto, and all wherewith they become tempted, or aſſaulted in their hearts.</hi> And in their louely ſociety,<note place="margin">Spirit. land. Cap. <hi>37.</hi> ſect. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>they doe not vow, or binde themſelues in the matrimony of men, nor yet ſuffer themſelues to be bound therein, but are like the Angels of Heauen. And there is no man that claymeth any thing to bee his owne, as to poſſeſſe the ſame to his owne priuate vſe; for no man, and that out of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones good diſpoſition, can deſire any thing to bee his owne, or yet to make any thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to himſelfe, from another; But alſo whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is there, is free; and is left free, in his vpright forme; There is alſo no man denyed to vſe any thing in freedome, of all that is profitable, and needfull for him, for they ſtand all in equity as one in the Loue, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:19298:49"/>
               <p> Oh who would haue thought that ſo many abhominations had lurked in this wicked Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily! though alas theſe bee not all that are knowne; and how many moe are vnknowne,<note place="margin">Pro. of H.N. Cap. <hi>22.</hi> ſect. <hi>16.</hi> and keepe ſecrets from vnbeleeuers.</note> men may imagine, <hi>by H.Ns. teaching his fellow Elders not to reueale their ſecrets, no, not to their owne young ones.</hi> This is <hi>H. Ns.</hi> light brought into the world in theſe latter times: but wee hope none of this new light, or rather darknes, will be ſheltred in the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayer Booke, It will not patronage any of theſe fearefull blaſphemies, and therefore the hypocriticall boldnes of theſe Familiſts will haue little thankes for this their affirmation: but before they come to this Light, obſerue what they muſt doe. <hi>Looke who ſo will know theſe thinges, muſt depart from all the wiſdome of the Learned, from the ſteps of the graue Fathers; and from the religious walkings of all the Deuout perſons, euen all the knowledge men haue, muſt away by little and little, from euery one that ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M. P. bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light. cap. <hi>7.</hi> ſect. <hi>23</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but before a Wiſe man can let ſlip all, there muſt riſe many agonies, anguiſhes, ſtriuings, and Earthquakes, &amp;c. For before the Truth ſhall appeare, the Deſtroyer muſt come and make all waſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All light of Truth muſt bee put out, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can come to theſe thinges. Oh feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wickednes!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:19298:50"/>
               <head>Tenthly, yee are voyde of the Chriſtian Faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> OF the Faith of <hi>H. Ns.</hi> Chriſt, we confeſſe our ſelues vtterly voide, and doe bleſſe our God for the ſame; but wee hauing manifeſted our Faith in the true <hi>Chriſt,</hi> none will iudge vs to be voyde thereof, but Atheiſticall Familiſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Eleauenthly, yee ſeperate from the holy Catholike Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> FIrſt let it be obſerued, what theſe Familiſts iudge of all that beleeue not the Loue. Thus they write; <hi>All ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not the Loue, nor are Baptiſed into the name of the Father, it is not meete to account ſuch vnbeleeuers and vnbaptiſed ones, for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, at whoſe hands wee ſhould looke for any word of truth, let them eſteeme themſelues as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as they will, they are a falſe Chriſtianity and deuilliſh Synagogue or Schoole:</hi> now this being their cenſure of all but themſelues. If they meane the holy Catholike Church to be the Family of Loue, as indeed <hi>H. N.</hi> ſaith, then we muſt beare this accuſation; For as wee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were of it, ſo we purpoſe to be deuided from it for euer. If they meane any other Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, how are they confounded, to call that the holy Catholike Church in one place, which
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19298:50"/>in another place they call a falſe Chriſtianity, and a deuilliſh Synagogue or Schoole; can the Deuils Synagogue be a holy Church? But if the Family or any other bee a deuilliſh Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, Gods people are commaunded to ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from them in all Spirituall fellowſhip; <hi>Seperate your ſelues from this froward generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.40.</note> 
                  <hi>haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull works of darknes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 5.11. 1. Cor. 10.20.</note> 
                  <hi>I would not yee ſhould haue fellowſhip with Deuils in the Sacrifices of the Gentiles. What fellowſhip hath Chriſt with the Deuill? the Beleeeuer with the vnbeleeuer; the Temple of God with Idols; Therefore ſeperate your ſelues ſaith the Lord, touch no vncleane thing, and I will receiue you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.14 &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>and bee a God and Father vnto you, and yee ſhall be my Sonnes and Daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus is ſeperation lawfull, till they haue proued that to be the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which they ſay we ſeperate from, which we truſt they ſhall neuer haue cauſe to accuſe vs of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Twelthly, there is not any one of you that is a new Creature.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> VVHat <hi>H.Ns.</hi> new Creature is, all may perceiue, where hee ſaith;<note place="margin">Crying voyce, Cap. vil. ſect. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>For to become waſhed in the Loue with her pure water, is the vpright waſhing, and the true font of the Regeneration or new Birth.</hi> And the <hi>ſecond Birth out of the Holy Ghoſt is in the Old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19298:51"/>of time, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dayes of the patience of Chriſt, in the obedience of the holy and Gracious word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exhort.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>ſect.</hi> 29.31.</note> 
                  <hi>and her ſeruice of Loue, are fulfilled, that then the holy Ghoſt beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth powred forth through Ieſus Chriſt, ouer them all that haue followed Chriſt in the Death of his Croſſe obediently, and haue kept his Doctrine (namely H.Ns.) with the word of his patience euen vnto the end,</hi> which is euery where taught in his tedious and intricate writings, the eſtate of <hi>Perfection</hi> in the loue, or Doctrine of this deceiuer. For he ſaith, <hi>The ſecond Birth which is not minded according to the Fleſh, but according to the Spirit of the heauenly Truth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth the victory, beareth rule with God, and bringeth forth the Name of</hi> Iſraell <hi>or</hi> Chriſt <hi>it ſelfe, as before hath beene related vpon another occaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This their Godded eſtate, is their ſecond birth or new Creature, which we doe much abhorre, and therfore no maruaile, if they ſay of vs, that not any one of vs are new creatures; But ſuch new creatures as the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſpeaketh of, that we imbrace and follow after, that being <hi>ſometimes fooliſh, diſobedient, deceiued, ſeruing diuers luſts and pleaſures, liuing in malice and enuy, hatefull, and hating one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but after that the kindneſſe and loue of God our Sauiour towards man appeared,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 3.3.4.5</note> 
                  <hi>not by the workes of righteouſnes which wee had done, but according to his mercy he ſaued vs by the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19298:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>waſhing of Regeneration and renuing of the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi> Hereby in a meaſure are wee new Creatures,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.13.</note> not now <hi>giuing our members ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of ſinne,</hi> nor taking pleaſure in any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes as before wee did; but endeauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring henceforth <hi>to giue our members ſeruants of righteouſnes in Holines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.1. &amp;c.</note> and <hi>to cleanſe our ſelues of all filthineſſe of Fleſh and Spirit, and to growe vp vnto perfect holineſſe in the feare of God.</hi> For our helpes herein, hauing not onely the power of the Spirit of God in our hearts; but alſo all thoſe bleſſed rules in Chriſts Teſtament, for the guidance of vs in the way of life; in which eſtate of Regeneration ſome are Babes:<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.12. &amp;c.</note> ſome are Young-men: and ſome may bee called Fathers, in reſpect of a meaſure of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, whereunto they may attaine, onely through <hi>Chriſts</hi> perfection, without whoſe perfection all mens perfection, is imperfection: through him, all his, <hi>Are able to doe all thinges:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4.13. Ioh. 15.5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>without him they can doe nothing.</hi> The weakeſt of his members are perfect with God through him, the ſtrongeſt are not perfect without him. For onely through him the Father is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and <hi>he is our Iuſtification,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30</note> and all in all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. But that any man can attaine vnto ſuch an eſtate in this life, as it is not poſſible for him to tranſgreſſe any Law of God by any meanes in thought, word, or deed, wee leaue that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilliſh Dreame with <hi>H. N.</hi> and his bewitched
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19298:52"/>followers, who account this the ſecond Birth or new Creature. The Apoſtles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the contrary. <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.2. &amp; 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>To theſe 12. ſuppoſed euils which in writing they haue taxed vs with, we will adde a 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. which we had fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their mouthes, and it is this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> You obſerue not the Commaundement gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the Woman and her ſeede, <hi>Reuel. 12.</hi> of flying into the Wildernes from the preſence of the Serpent.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> THeir meaning is, that wee are too open in our profeſſion, through the which we endure much miſery; for ſo they haue ſaid vnto vs, they would haue vs diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble like themſelues, and ſaue our ſelues from troubles. For <hi>M. P.</hi> who calleth himſelfe that mighty Prince of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> in his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Croſſe corrected, Thus he writeth; <hi>It is written,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>3.</hi> ſect. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſaying; When they perſecute you in this Citty flye into another; that is: whileſt wee are yet weake, &amp; not well able to beare the croſſe; we may doe as</hi> Peter <hi>did, with mouth deny Chriſt, but not in heart.</hi> And much more of this ſtuffe he proceedeth in; but in diuers places of the margent, he writeth; <hi>Hide ſecrets from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers.</hi> To whom wee may ſay, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> when hee diſſwaded him from Suffering; <hi>Get thee behinde me Sathan, thou art an offence vnto me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>thou vnderſtandeſt not the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19298:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>thinges that are of God, &amp;c.</hi> Are not Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants <hi>the ſalt of the earth? and the light of the world? ſhall the light be put vnder a Buſhell?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and not ſet on a Candleſticke. Chriſt</hi> commands that <hi>what he ſaid in Darknes, that his ſhould ſpeake it in the Light; and what they heard in the eare, that they ſhould Preach on the houſes; and not feare them that would kill the Body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 10. c.</note> 
                  <hi>and after that could doe no more.</hi> For he <hi>that is aſhamed of Chriſt and his words,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 8.38</note> 
                  <hi>amongſt this Adulterous and ſinfull generation, of him ſhall the Sonne of man be aſhamed, when he commeth in the Glory of his Father with his holy Angels:</hi> For as <hi>with the heart man beleeueth vnto righteouſnes, ſo with the mouth, he muſt confeſſe to ſaluation;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10.10</note> 
                  <hi>If we ſuffer with Chriſt, we ſhall raigne with Chriſt, and if we deny him, he will deny vs;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.12</note> This the true <hi>Chriſt</hi> teacheth whom wee confeſſe and endeauour to ſerue: But <hi>H. N.</hi> and the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies Chriſt teacheth them to ſaue themſelues, and rather to diſſemble if Authority command it, then ſuffer any afflictions to the outward man, abuſing for his purpoſe this Scripture, <hi>Bleſſed is the barren, that beareth not, &amp;c.</hi> As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>that Chriſts yoake is eaſie, and his burthen light;</hi> And therefore bringeth not his, to ſuffer perſecution to the outward man, but to doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that Authority commaundeth, whoſe groſſe abhominations hath been formerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, and we truſt our innocency defended, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19298:53"/>all the accuſations of theſe Children of that olde accuſer of the Brethren. The Lord diſcouer their moſt palpable abhominations, and deliuer poore ſimple ſoules from their ſnares,<note place="margin">Pro. 9.18.</note> for aſſuredly <hi>the Dead are there, and her gueſts are in the depth of Hell.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>IF theſe <hi>Familiſts,</hi> or any that are not willing to be knowne to be of them, doe except a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any thing either by word or writing, which is here written, and ſay that we wrong them, in alledging <hi>H. Ns.</hi> and the reſt, their helliſh ſayings, and laying them vpon them; we anſwer them, many of theſe ſayings are their owne, and all the reſt for any thing that we knowe, for otherwiſe they would not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſe their Bookes, if they did not approue of the Doctrine contained in them, &amp; in all things that we know follow their courſe; and we har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily beſeech all that ſhall haue to deale with them; that if they be aſhamed of <hi>H. N.</hi> and this his new light or euerlaſting <hi>Goſpell,</hi> which they ſo much glory of, that they would require them, by writing to be publiſhed, to teſtifie their abhorring of theſe his wicked blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, otherwiſe they will not onely confirme all, of their holding the ſame; but alſo giue all occaſion to iudge them to bee as they are, diſſembling hypocrites, who hold thinges, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19298:53"/>yet endeauour to perſwade people that they doe not holde them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Let them teſtifie their abhorring.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1. FIrſt that which</hi> H. N. <hi>hath written of God,</hi> That God and Man had one Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Spirit, Nature and being; that God was all that Man was, and Man was all that God was.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> That <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Perfection in the Louely being, whereunto their Godded Elders doe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: Or any power in man, whereby hee can keepe the Law, without Faith in the man <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> That the true Baptiſme is: To bee in the loue and her Seruice.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> That the Reſurrection of the Dead: The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Iudgement: and the euerlaſting life, is in this life before the naturall Death of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: And that the Body commeth to nothing after Death.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5.</hi> That they ought to proſtrate their Bodyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Idoll or Idol-ſeruice, at the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates command, keeping their hearts to God.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6.</hi> That the Worſhip of God, ſtandeth not at all, in any outward Ordinance or obſeruation.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7.</hi> That if one bee tempted to any Sinne and cry, and there come no helpe; hee or ſhe is guiltleſſe though they commit the Act.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8.</hi> That they doe not binde themſelues in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19298:54"/>of men, nor yet ſuffer themſelues to be bound therein, but are like the Angels of Heauen.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9.</hi> That they ought to confeſſe before the Eldeſt in the Family, all their euill thoughts, wordes, and deedes whatſoeuer they be, and all that their inclination and Nature draweth them vnto.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>10.</hi> That ſome of them are come vnto ſuch a perfection, that being Godded with God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thought, word, nor deed, they can ſinne any more.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>11.</hi> That no man maketh any thing his owne, or proper to himſelfe, but all thinges whatſoeuer is in the Loue, is free, and is as one.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>12.</hi> That any that are ignorant though Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and worſhippers of Deuils, and iuſtifying themſelues therein, may bee ſaued; though they know not nor beleeue in the Blood of the man <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>13.</hi> That H. N: M. P. and the ſeruant of M. P. were raiſed vp of God, to publiſh theſe thinges to the world, in theſe latter dayes as an euerlaſting <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>All theſe thinges hath</hi> Henry Nicholas <hi>and his followers publiſhed, being raiſed vp out of the infernall pit, to the deceiuing of them that beleeue not the Truth,</hi> (<hi>which</hi> Ieſus Chriſt <hi>the Sonne of the Eternall Father hath reuealed</hi>)
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19298:54"/>
                  <hi>but haue pleaſure in vnrighteouſnes, being of God deliuered vp to a reprobate minde, that they might be damned. If they teſtifie their abhorring of theſe thinges, without ſcores eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or mentall reſeruation, we ſhall be glad: If not; let them be content to be called his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, whoſe Diſcipline they maintaine. Wee doe herein, as we would be done vnto, for we are content that any whatſoeuer, ſhall aske vs a reaſon of our Faith, in any thing, and we will render it to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now the Lord</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>the great and good Shepheard of his Sheepe, diſcloſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the lyes and ſnares of this Theefe and robber</hi> H. N. <hi>and his followers, that the ſoules of all for whom</hi> Chriſt <hi>hath payed ſo deare a price, may be deliuered from their deſtruction, and be brought vnto and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in his Folde, to their Immortality of ſoule and body, in Glory euerlaſting, By the ſame our Lord and Sauiour, to whome with the Father, and the bleſſed Spirit, one Eternall, and euerliuing God, be Glory and Dominion, now and for euer.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19298:55"/>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 111.104.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>By thy precepts J haue gotten vnderſtanding: therefore J hate all the wayes of falſhood.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>VERS. 115.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Away from me yee wicked; for I will keepe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of my God.</p>
               </q>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:19298:55"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
